<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The saints sufferings, and sinners sorrowes. Or, The evident tokens of the salvation of the one, and the perdition of the other Phil. I.28, 2 Thes. I.6,7</title>
            <author>Yates, John, d. ca. 1660.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1631</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 215 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 186 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A15826</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 26087</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S101332</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99837148</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99837148</idno>
            <idno type="VID">1458</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A15826)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 1458)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 981:03)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The saints sufferings, and sinners sorrowes. Or, The evident tokens of the salvation of the one, and the perdition of the other Phil. I.28, 2 Thes. I.6,7</title>
                  <author>Yates, John, d. ca. 1660.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[70], 282 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by T. Cotes, for N. Bourne, dwelling in the Royall Exchange,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1631.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>By John Yates.</note>
                  <note>Some print faded and show-through; some pages stained.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Dr. Williams' Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Salvation --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sin --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:1458:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:1458:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE SAINTS SVFFERINGS, and Sinners Sorrowes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Or,</hi> The evident tokens of the ſalvation of the one, and the perdition of the other, <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.28, 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.6, 7.</p>
            <q>Sanctorum Victima, victoria <bibl>Rom. 8.36, 37. 2 Cor. 4.8.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>Impiorum Laetitia luctus. <bibl>Iam. 4.9. &amp; 5.1.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Ambr.</bibl> 
               <p>
                  <hi>Melius &amp; falieius eſt pugna<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tem non vinci, quam deſidem non tentari.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Impij per multa pericula perveniunt ad plura, per plura ad peſsima.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>T. Cotes,</hi> for <hi>N. Bourne,</hi> dwelling at the Royall Exchange. 1631.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:1458:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:1458:2"/>
            <head>To the truly Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable, and Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious Sir <hi>Roger Townſend,</hi> &amp; Sir <hi>Robert Crane,</hi> Knights and Baronets, and their Noble and vertuous Ladies, increaſe of joy and peace in beleeving.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Honorable, and worthy Witneſſes.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Crave your teſtimonies, as well for
<pb facs="tcp:1458:3"/>the preaching, as the printing of theſe Sermons. You were at ſundry times, and in ſeverall places, the beſt and chiefeſt of my hearers, and it concernes your ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours to be as inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent in the hearing as it was my duty to be innocent in the ſpeaking. You cannot be ignorant of the Accuſation,
<pb facs="tcp:1458:3"/>and if that were ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient to make a man guilty,
<note place="margin">Si accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaſſe ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiat, qui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> erit Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cens?</note> who ſhould be innocent? as once <hi>Julian</hi> ſaid of the Chriſtians, the worſt man of the beſt living.</p>
            <p>It is the ſaying of <hi>Syracides.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 11.7.</note> Blame not before thou haſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amined the truth: underſtand firſt, and then rebuke. It was the ſharpe cenſure
<pb facs="tcp:1458:4"/>of King <hi>James</hi> in his <hi>Daemonology,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lib. 3. Cap. 1.</note> that <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certaine report, is the authour of all lies:</hi> yet they are worſe who <hi>lye in wait to finde fault and to turne good into evill,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ecclus 11 31.</note> of whom the wiſe man hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained long ſince, and we may ſee how every age of the world renders it, day by day more malicious.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:1458:4"/>
            <p>Alas, when there is wanting that ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue which in all men we call <hi>Honeſty:</hi> and that ſpeciall gift of God which in Chriſtians wee call <hi>Charity,</hi> how are men condemned without hearing, and wounded with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out offence given? We ſee in experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, that dogges al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes barke at
<pb facs="tcp:1458:5"/>thoſe they know not, and that it is their nature to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>company one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in thoſe cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mors: ſo is it with the inconſiderate multitude, being once ſet on, they truſt to their tongs, their teeth are gone, and barke and bleat when they cannot bite.</p>
            <p>It is a pennance
<pb facs="tcp:1458:5"/>to a Preacher to bee troubled with tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flers, who have neither eyes to ſee, nor heads to appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend what is ſaid; yet dare they thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and threaten, as if they meant to beare downe all be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them: Every underſtanding hath a peculiar judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, by which it anſwereth other me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,
<pb facs="tcp:1458:6"/>and valueth it ſelfe; and therefore it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſeeme ſtrange to me to be abuſed by reports. Let vaine men pricke on in their pride, hoyſe up the top-ſayle of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truth, and flant it out againſt us, yet God forbid, that theſe ſhould al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes have wind at will, and finde as free paſſage to ſupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riours
<pb facs="tcp:1458:6"/>as they ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine. But ſeeing it is ſo eaſie to faine, and face out re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports, I muſt be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to leave ſuch profeſſors, to their eaſie wayes of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion, than the which, there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of more frail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie.</p>
            <p>When <hi>Moſes</hi> ſaw the <hi>Jſraelite,</hi> and the <hi>Aegyptian</hi> fight, hee
<pb facs="tcp:1458:7"/>did not ſay, <hi>Why ſtrive you?</hi> but drew his ſword, and ſlew the <hi>Aegyptian:</hi> but when hee ſaw two <hi>Iſraelites</hi> quarrell, he ſaid, <hi>Yee are brethren, why ſtrive you?</hi> If any thing delivered bee an <hi>Aegyptian,</hi> let it be ſlaine by the ſword of the Spirit, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver reconciled: but if an <hi>Jſraelite,</hi> and yet queſtioned, why
<pb facs="tcp:1458:7"/>ſtrive you? What wrong I have done, let all judge that reade this Sermon: what wrong is done to mee by the accuſation, Heave to him, that either mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtooke me, or meant me a miſchiefe. Hee hath put an <hi>Aegypti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> in the place of an <hi>Jſraelite,</hi> and an er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour in the place of a truth. I ſaid, <hi>God is
<pb facs="tcp:1458:8"/>often a mothe in our counſels,</hi> meaning in the ſucceſſe, and event of mans con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſultations, which to be an <hi>Iſraelite,</hi> theſe Scriptures doe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge, <hi>Deut.</hi> 28.28. <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 5.12. <hi>Zach.</hi> 12.4. How theſe words may be ſtrained to Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels of State (as they are by my accuſer) I confeſſe it paſſeth
<pb facs="tcp:1458:8"/>my underſtanding.</p>
            <p>It may be the failes and follies of ſome in preaching, to ſeeke vulgar ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plauſe; A vanity much avoyded by wiſe men. <hi>Saint Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gustine</hi> affirmed,
<note place="margin">Laudari a bon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> timeo, &amp; amari a ma io de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtor.</note> that <hi>he feared the praiſe of good men, and detested that of evill.</hi> And to them that will reade and remember, our ancients have given
<pb facs="tcp:1458:9"/>better rules. Saint <hi>Ierom</hi> deſired in prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching,
<note place="margin">Hier ad Nep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t. Lachryma auditorum ſunt lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des tua. Non pla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum, ſed planctum.</note> rather to have the <hi>praiſe of the teares than of the tongues o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> his hearers.</hi> Saint <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine</hi> being applau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded for his prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching, anſweres: <hi>F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia haec ſunt, nos fructu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> quaerimus. Theſe a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> but leaves, we looke fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> fruit. Chryſoſtome</hi> tol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> his hearers, <hi>he ow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> them thanks, when th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:1458:9"/>payed him teares. Si haec audientes, doletis, maximas me debere vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis gratias confiteor, quis eſt enim qui melae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificat, niſi qui contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>statur ex me?</hi> Theſe rules ſhall I deſire to follow both in preaching; and in printing, and for this end I have deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, to make my thoughts more legi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and my ſelfe
<pb facs="tcp:1458:10"/>and my Sermons, the ſubject of every opinion, wiſe, or weake.</p>
            <p>I have preſumed vpon the Dedicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and having thought upon ſome Witneſſes and Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trons, have addreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed my ſelfe to ſuch friends, as love the truth, and deſerve to be loved of it. I wil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> not trouble you o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:1458:10"/>any other with fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther reaſons of my writing, or with ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſes. He that doth ill, no plea can war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant him: and hee that doth well, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not eaſily be diſcou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged with any cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures. I crave no mans pardon in gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving good counſell, but his acceptation; And preſents of love may be well ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken
<pb facs="tcp:1458:11"/>both of friends and ſtrangers. The things I dare ſay, are both <hi>commoda, &amp; ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodata,</hi> ſeaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and profitable for our times, wher<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in God ſmiteth, and his houſhold ſmar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teth; and ſuch begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings will have feareful endings up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their enemies.</p>
            <p>An heathen wiſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> man could ſay, Ad<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>verſities
<pb facs="tcp:1458:11"/>are <hi>Tributa vivendi,</hi> tributes of living. And wiſe Chriſtians above all ought to know them, and to pay them moſt willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. Their Lord and maſter hath gone before them, and it is their duty to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low him, not as thoſe whining ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers, <hi>qui gementes ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quuntur Imperatorem;</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:1458:12"/>but as thoſe worthy Martyrs, which like a cloud of witneſſes, have gone before them. And here I reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber ſome paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages that may bee patterns for others, which I have heard from ſome of you, well agreeing with the ſubject of my Text,
<note place="margin">Dicta do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cta &amp; pia <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> verè diligentis deum, &amp; Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am,</note> as namely: <hi>He will never dye for Chriſt, that will not
<pb facs="tcp:1458:12"/>firſt learne to live for him.</hi> Another of the like nature was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning comfort in death. <hi>videl. Death takes away the pleaſure of all worldly things, and Religion the paine of death.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This may well make us prize the rule of the Apoſtle, that <hi>Godlineſſe is great gaine,</hi> and ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a godly life is to
<pb facs="tcp:1458:13"/>be preferred before all good things a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout us. VVhat can it advantage a man to be well for the world, and ill, and vile for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe? He gaines no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing that wins the world, with the loſſe of himſelfe. Very Ethnicks in their Ethickes have laid it downe for a rule, that nothing is
<pb facs="tcp:1458:13"/>ſo good for a man as to live well. Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, riches, plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, have their va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luations in the world, and they are the greateſt markes men ſhoot at, and ſtraine their conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences to the higheſt. But howſoever men give theſe their good word, yet they will be wanting in the day of death,
<pb facs="tcp:1458:14"/>when nothing but the gaine of godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe will profit us.</p>
            <p>To purchaſe ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, we make ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches our ſervants; and yet even this conſiſteth for the moſt part in the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plauſe of the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, which it may be will follow us in faire weather; but will be ſure to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake us in the firſt
<pb facs="tcp:1458:14"/>tempeſt of misfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, and ſteere a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way before the Sea, and wind, leaving us to the rualice of our deſtinies. Who would truſt ſuch an heard of Animals, that pleaſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves with the noiſe they make, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any true know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the cauſe, or the diſtinction of vertue and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune?
<pb facs="tcp:1458:15"/>Let the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pious proſper, and they ſhall be applau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded; and let the ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous be unhappy, and they ſhall bee deſpiſed. Fortune raiſeth up men to the horſe, and rideth them: who when they are deſcended, and on foot like o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther men, and they and their fortune parted, we ſhall ſee
<pb facs="tcp:1458:15"/>a bitter contempt ſpurne at the one with as great liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, as a baſe Groome dare preſume to beat the other. Who ſeeth not then the profit of Godlineſſe to be preferred, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all worldly ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages?</p>
            <p>That skill muſt needes be the beſt, which can teach a man to know him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe,
<pb facs="tcp:1458:16"/>and that gaine the greateſt, which is acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>panied with the favour of God, grace of Chriſt, and comfort of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and which can made us bleſſed in this life, and the life to come. The Saints ſufferings, and Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners ſorrowes, have co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary beginnings, and contrary en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings. Their be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginnings
<pb facs="tcp:1458:16"/>are known by their ſhortneſſe, their endings can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be knowne for their Eternity. A good man knowes the worſt at the firſt, and his very ſorrow is turned in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to joy, and his joy is unſpeakeable and glorious: but a wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked man knowes his beſt at the firſt, and his joy is turned
<pb facs="tcp:1458:17"/>into ſorrow, and his ſorrow is not to bee defined. All that our Text can ſay of it, is, <hi>What ſhall his end bee?</hi> Nay, there is yet more both in their joy and ſorrow. It is not an alteration, but a converſion. A good mans ſorrow is not onely chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, and removed; but converted into
<pb facs="tcp:1458:17"/>joy, as the matter of it: but the joy of the wicked is not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly taken away, but made the matter of his future ſorrow, and oftentimes as an unknowne ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row ſprings from an unknowne ſin, as we ſhall diſcover in a ſecond Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon.</p>
            <p>The joy and woe of this world, how
<pb facs="tcp:1458:18"/>great ſoever, will ſaile out of ſight; and then death which purſues us, and keepes us in chaſe, will lay hold, and faſten on our bodies, as priſes for wormes, and leave our ſoules to a worſe reckoning. O what an extreame madneſſe were it, in the ſhipwracke of all worldly things,
<pb facs="tcp:1458:18"/>where all ſinkes but the ſorrow, to ſave that for another world? What then remaines to him that all his life hath injoyed fortune for a ſervant, and time for a friend, but the heavy, ſecret, ſad, and ſevere thoughts of another life, where neither Time nor Fortune ſhall favour him? Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py
<pb facs="tcp:1458:19"/>are all thoſe that have grace to value worldly vanities, at no more than their owne price, and by retaining the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable memory of a well-acted life, can behold death with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out dread, and the grave without feare, and imbrace both as neceſſary guides to endleſſe glory.</p>
            <p>The ſorrowes of
<pb facs="tcp:1458:19"/>this life, are but of two ſorts; The one hath reſpect to God, when we complain to him againſt our ſelves, and for our offences, count him juſt in all that wee ſuffer; and to ſuch ſorrow Saint <hi>Paul</hi> hath promiſed bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedneſſe. The other hath reſpect to the world, when wee mutter to our ſelves
<pb facs="tcp:1458:20"/>againſt God, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> complaine of him as if hee had don<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> us wrong, either it not giving, or ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king away what we deſire to have an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to hold: forgettin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> that humble and ju<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> acknowledgment o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> holy <hi>Job, The Lor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> hath given, and th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Lord hath taken, bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed be the Name of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Lord.</hi> And ſuch ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row
<pb facs="tcp:1458:20"/>the Apoſtle <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ath threatned with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eath.</p>
            <p>Queſtionleſſe hee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s either a foole, or a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ebell that wil quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ell with God in his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>avours, or frownes. A foole, if he be ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant whence bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings and croſſes come: a rebell, if he know it, and bee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>mpatient. How meane ſoever our
<pb facs="tcp:1458:21"/>eſtate be, yet is th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſame farre greate<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> than that w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> oweth us; and ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſharpe ſoever o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> afflictions be, yet th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſame are farre leſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> than thoſe whic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> are due unto us. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> know impatience full of excuſes, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> wee ſay wee rath<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> murmure at th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> hand, than the pow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>er that beats us: b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:1458:21"/>take heed, leſt like ſome fooliſh Curres whilſt we bite the ſtone, wee barke a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the hand that threw it. See God in all his chaſtiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and beare with patience, for whatſoever the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning is, the end ſhall be happy.</p>
            <p>To conclude, My deſire is to all, and you in ſpeciall, for
<pb facs="tcp:1458:22"/>the acceptation, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſall, and Patro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage of theſe Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons. It is but a ſmall teſtimony o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> my unfained obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance of you, and al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> that love the truth<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> And thus I take my leave, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend both you, and yours to the God o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> mercy, and truth, who guide, comfort, deliver, ſanctifie,
<pb facs="tcp:1458:22"/>and preſerve you all, and fill you with the comforts of the bleſſed hope of the appearing of Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours in the ſervice of Ieſus Chriſt, to be ever commanded, <hi>JOHN YATES.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="authors_note">
            <pb facs="tcp:1458:23"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:1458:23"/>
            <head>The Authors ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertiſement.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>WHEN the Philoſopher ſpake ſoberly to the people,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Laert. in vita Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>og. lib.</hi> 6.</note> they gave him no audience: but playing the Minſtrell, multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes flocked after him.</hi> Poets and Poe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizing
<pb facs="tcp:1458:24"/>prophets have preſumed to preach and prophecie of our calami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties; and we, like grace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe men, are well con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to reade them, and make merry with our owne miſeries, and to laugh at our owne miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunes. Wee are in juſt, and God is in good earnest, and in the end we ſhall know to our cost, what it is to trifle with God. God will
<pb facs="tcp:1458:24"/>bend us or breake us, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore either he ceaſe ſmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, or wee ſmarting. <hi>Bee afflicted,
<note place="margin">Iam. 4.9, 10.</note> and mourne, and weep, let your laughter be turned into lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, and your joy into heavineſſe. Humble your ſelves in the ſight of God, and he ſhall lift you up.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>J have laboured in this Treatiſe, to treade
<pb facs="tcp:1458:25"/>out a way before you, and even from the Saints ſufferings, and Sinners ſorrowes, to giue you good counſell. Now is the time to glorifie God in ſuffering, and by the beginnings of judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, to ſhew our ſelves to be of Gods fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milie. My Text is a Briefe of judgements, both upon Gods houſe, and upon the haters of it; and gives the true di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction
<pb facs="tcp:1458:25"/>of the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and end thereof. That judgement that begins with Gods peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, fals heavily in the end upon their enemies.</p>
            <p>J may ſeeme in the middle of this Treatiſe to forſake my Text to ſeeke out the Commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary: but J ſhall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat my Reader for a favourable expoſition of my minde and meaning. The Text toucheth the
<pb facs="tcp:1458:26"/>ſinne that ought to bee taught with all exact<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and therefore J to helpe my Reader the better, have bent my ſtrength the more to deale thorowly with it in all the branches. J ſhall eaſily render my account, and by that other Text, cleare my ſelfe of all unneceſſary digreſsions, and unprofi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table ſearches of ſuch ſecrets as that place J
<pb facs="tcp:1458:26"/>now mention, will allow me.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ioh. 16.7, 8.</hi> It is a truth that Chriſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts upon, that his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture is as expedient and neceſſary as his comming into the world. He came into the world to redeeme it, and hee leaves the world, that his Redemption may be preached and applyed. This application is the worke of the Spirit,
<pb facs="tcp:1458:27"/>and by conviction is to be wrought upon the world. The things of which the world is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced, are all Evange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licall, and eſſentially differ from things le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall. Firſt, in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, the Law com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands us <hi>to doe and live,</hi> the Goſpel, <hi>to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve and live.</hi> The Law bids us looke <hi>to our owne righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe;</hi> The Goſpel
<pb facs="tcp:1458:27"/>
               <hi>to the righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of Chriſt.</hi> The Law does charge us <hi>with holineſſe, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to our own righteouſneſſe.</hi> The Goſpel, <hi>with holines according to the Spirit:</hi> Which being more exact, is the cauſe that it is ſo much ſpur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned at, and contemned by the world. Legall purity is not perſecuted like Evangelicall puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.
<pb facs="tcp:1458:28"/>A man may bee a Phariſee, and favoured by the world: but a ſtrict Chriſtian is out of hope to farewell, even by the beſt worldlings. Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution hath waited more upon the Goſpel, than the Law. The light of the one is farre too cleare for worldly eyes to behold it. Jt is ſtrange with the world to deny it ſelfe, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve in another. Jt is
<pb facs="tcp:1458:28"/>hard to forſake a morall righteouſneſſe, and ſeek to be juſtified by ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Who can indure to have Satan ſo judged in him, as quite to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake all Lawes, as to live by the new Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement? This is a large difference of le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall and Evangelicall commands: yet let them be accurſed, that ſo farre ſet at oddes Law and Goſpel, as either like
<pb facs="tcp:1458:29"/>
               <hi>Iewes</hi> doe reject the Goſpel to defend the Law, or like Familiſts renounce the Law to maintaine the Goſpel. Love and no Law is the lewd learning of our new Goſpellers. Duty, ſay they, is not worth the name of a Chriſtian, that muſt doe all of meere love. Looſe love that likes of nothing but free will offerings. Such licences are not granted
<pb facs="tcp:1458:29"/>by Law or Goſpel. They both agree in the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of our lives, and yeeld us liberty to obey, no licence to live as wee liſt: The Law will ſend us to Christ, and the Chriſtian being ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtied, will be ſent backe againe by the Goſpel, to walke unblameably by the Law.</p>
            <p>Legall comminati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons follow our workes, and curſe us for our
<pb facs="tcp:1458:30"/>deedes: but legall com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations follow our ſaith, and where that is wanting, tell us wee are condemned, and as ſure to goe to hell, as if wee were there already. Legall promiſes of life depend upon our merits, and tell us we ſhall bee rewarded for our well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doing. But Evange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licall promiſes depend upon our faith and Christs merit, and tels
<pb facs="tcp:1458:30"/>us it ſhall be onely well with us in him. Sinnes wee have againſt the Law, and every booke intreats of them. Sinnes wee have againſt the Goſpel, and it were well every Writer would in theſe dayes inſiſt upon them. J have ventured farre into their diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, and wiſh all Chriſtians by the exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of the <hi>Iewes</hi> in my Text, to take heed of
<pb facs="tcp:1458:31"/>them. There is one thing will bee admired at, both for the Method and matter; how J come to ſpeake ſo much; and in ſuch a manner, of the glorious kingdome of the bleſſed Trinitie. My anſwer will be ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, having granted me the Commentary for my Text. The holy Ghoſt comes in the ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of Chriſt, and by applying his redempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
<pb facs="tcp:1458:31"/>adminiſters firſt in the kingdome of God, taking poſſeſsion of thoſe ſubjects that God the Father hath choſen, and whom JESVS Chriſt hath redeemed by his precious blood. The Spirit workes for the Sonne, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore returnes the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome to him againe at his ſecond comming. The Son works for the Father, and therefore ſo
<pb facs="tcp:1458:32"/>takes the Kingdome from the Spirit, that in the end he gives it up to the Father for the full perfection of glory. This mutuall working ſends me in my diſcourſe from one perſon to another, and to all the world, to let them ſee what may be gained or loſt, by obeying or diſobeying the Goſpell. I have wondred in reading the moſt ancient Fathers,
<pb facs="tcp:1458:32"/>what they meant by ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging ſo frequently men to Martyrdome, that they might not loſe the honour of riſing and reigning with Chriſt at his ſecond appearing. Surely they ſaw and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeved that the Spirit of grace did not in vaine perſwade them. They ſhall have honour accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to their hope, and as above others they gave their lives for
<pb facs="tcp:1458:33"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:1458:33"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:1458:34"/>Chriſt: ſo before others they ſeeme to live a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, <hi>Rev 20.4.</hi> Let the meaning in that place be what it will, for J will not determine thereof: yet the age of the ten perſecutions ſo conceived of it, as by plentifull teſtimonies might appeare. Jt is agreeable with Chriſts proceedings, to honour them that honour him, and as they are before
<pb facs="tcp:1458:34"/>others in their zeale and ſervice; ſo to be above others in their dignity and deſert, though not of merite, and for their workes; yet according to his mercy and their workes. J could not well leave untouched, with the comming of the holy Ghoſt, upon Chriſts departure, the returne of him againe, and deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very up of all to the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that the Family
<pb facs="tcp:1458:35"/>and Houſhold in my Text, might ſee their patience perfected in power, and their power conſummated in glory. The Kingdome of God in the divers admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrations of it, will bee worthy the contempla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and Gods Houſe ſhall bee moſt happy in their thoughts of it: All their enemies moſt miſerable in the loſſe and deprivation
<pb facs="tcp:1458:35"/>thereof. Their ends ſhall be augmented, in miſery as many degrees as that Kingdome ſhall bee ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanced in glory. But J will ſtay my Reader no longer in the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face, but wiſh him good ſucceſſe in the ſubſtance of that which follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:1458:36"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:1458:36"/>
            <head>THE SAINTS Sufferings.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>1 PET. 4.17.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>For the time is come, that judgement muſt beginne at the houſe of God: and if it firſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginne at us, what ſhall the end be of them, that obey not the Goſpel of God?</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen <hi>Samuel</hi> had fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed his ſpeech to <hi>Iſrael,</hi> God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe ſecondeth the Prophet with a voyce from
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:1458:37"/>heaven; and then the people tremble: 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 12.18. wee never have our hearers at an advantage till God make their eares to tingle with ſome judgement: then they ſtoup with <hi>Samuel,</hi> and ſay, <hi>Speake Lord, for thy Servants heare.</hi> The text I have now choſen, toucheth upon the things, which are both <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moda</hi> and <hi>accommodata,</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable and ſeaſonable for theſe times; wherein the houſe of God groaneth un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der affliction.</p>
            <p>Two purgatories attend and waite upon Gods fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in this world; one of <hi>water</hi> another of <hi>fire:</hi> and no ſooner are Gods ſervants waſhed with the water of baptiſme, but preſently they
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:1458:37"/>are caſt into the fire of af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction, and proved and try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as gold. Both are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed in this Chapter; the firſt to the 12. <hi>ver.</hi> and the ſecond from thence to the end. That we may have the <hi>mind of Chriſt, ceaſe from ſinne, and live to the will of God,</hi> the waſhing of the new birth is neceſſary: only the ſecond purgatory ſeemeth unquoth and ſtrange, that fyrie trialls ſhould befall innocencie, and the purity of Saints bee perſecuted by ſinners: but the reaſons of the Apoſtle will quiet this conceit, and comfort them: Firſt, with greater inward joy than any outward ſorrow can command, Verſ. 13. Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, with a greater fulneſſe
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:1458:38"/>of glory than any malice can obſcure, the very ſpirit of glory reſteth upon them, that the worſt of tongues can never wipe off, Verſ. 14. Thirdly, with a better cauſe than contumelie can con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer, Verſ 15.16. Fourthly, with a ſweeter ſeaſon than ſorrowes can ſowre, Ver. 17. And this reaſon the text al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgeth, out of which I will rayſe theſe five propoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>God hath a houſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>God judgeth his houſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>God in judgeing makes Choyce of a fit time.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>God having a fit time, doth but begin with his houſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>Where God begins to judge, he makes there an end.</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:1458:38"/>
               <head>God hath a houſe.</head>
               <p>The ſenſe of this propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is plainely and fully ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed in 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.15. <hi>That thou maieſt know how thou oughteſt to behave thy ſelfe in the houſe of God, which is the Church of the living God.</hi> This houſe then is the Church; a holy, ſpirituall, living and growing houſe 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.5. <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.21. No houſe in the world, that is honoured with theſe properties be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides: and therefore fitteſt for the holy, ſpirituall, and living God to dwell in. Other houſes are all mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall and corporall; wherein God is neither included, nor out of which he can be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded, in regard of his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite eſſence: though in the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:1458:39"/>manifeſtation of his eſſence hee reſideth ever in his Church after a tranſcendent manner. Where ſhall a mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter moſt delight to be, but at home? and what home hath God: but his Church? <hi>The earth is the Lords and the fulneſſe of it:</hi> but the Church is his ſpeciall poſſeſſion, and the manſion of his glory.</p>
               <p>The Church is Gods houſe, becauſe he is both owner and maker of it. The Lord (if you marke it) is maiſter of his houſe, not af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the cuſtome of men; who firſt owne and then build; for God ſhould have nothing to owne, did hee not firſt make. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 100.3. <hi>He hath made us, and not we our ſelves, we are his people and
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:1458:39"/>the ſheepe of his Paſture.</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide this grand title, God makes challenge to his Church by other rightfull claimes; as election, <hi>Amos</hi> 3.2. by redemption, <hi>Tit.</hi> 2.14. Proviſion, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 31.19.84.11. protection, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 31.5.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſes in reſpect of the houſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holder.</head>
               <p>Vſe 1. To <hi>caſt our care up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on God;</hi> who being maiſter of his family will take care for it. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.7. Caſting preſuppoſeth confidence; for he that doubteth, will ſcarce reſt ſecurely on God: Like as a man that treadeth on the Ice and quaketh at the leaſt cracking, will bee loth to caſt downe his body, where he feareth to venture
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:1458:40"/>his foot. But we need not be timorous, when wee are to caſt our care upon God; but may truſt him with our bodies and ſoules, and then try him; as the maiſter of that houſehold, whereof we are members.</p>
               <p>Secondly, It muſt alſo teach us holineſſe, for holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe becommeth Gods houſe for ever. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 93.5. Hence is it, that the Lord lets the wicked lie unclean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, as habitations unfit for the majeſtie of heaven, and therefore ſuffred to drop downe in their owne rot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenneſſe and corruption: but rather than his owne houſe ſhould not be clenſed, hee himſelfe will take his fanne and purge his ſloore; and
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:1458:40"/>handle the beſome to ſweep out every dirty and noy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome corner: yea hee will puniſh it, that hee may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fine and repaire it, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 27.9. Our pollutions in this kingdome muſt have a ſweeping; for the Lord ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving begun with us, if wee be his houſe, hee will not give over untill hee hath ſearched every corner and hallowed us to his owne uſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſes in reſpect of the family.</head>
               <p n="1">1. It muſt perſwade us to unity, the very ſight of two things in the houſe of God made <hi>Paul</hi> exceeding joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, <hi>Col.</hi> 2.5. <hi>faith</hi> and <hi>order:</hi> Faith makes faſt God and his houſe ſo firme in ſocie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, that nothing can devide
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:1458:41"/>them. Steadfaſtneſſe of faith makes Gods houſe ſtand and reſt immovable, yet would it be as a confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed heape, if order ſhould not beautifie it: Order ſets God in the family as Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, all other as ſervants, and teacheth us hee muſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, and wee obey, and happy is the family when it is ſo ordered. True faith and right order are the two grounded pillars for this houſe to reſt upon, which reeleth and is ready to fall upon their firſt and leaſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>movall. Wee muſt there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore take heed to the firſt and leaſt diſjoyning of theſe two; admit error or evill in eyther, and it will indan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger the whole. <hi>A houſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:1458:41"/>in it ſelfe cannot ſtand,</hi> our deviſions eyther in do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine or diſcipline make a rent in the houſe of God. By the one we weaken faith, and by the other the beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of order. Peace which all men call for, muſt bee grounded on theſe two pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars; no truth, no true peace; no order, no ſure peace; ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is it enough to have them in the Lawes of the family, but they muſt bee within, even in the heart and ſoules of all thoſe that will accord in one houſe.</p>
               <p>Alas, when we plead for peace, wee obſerve not the rule. <hi>Mar.</hi> 9.50. <hi>Have ſalt in your ſelves, and peace one with another.</hi> Vnſeaſoned and unſanctified men want the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:1458:42"/>true ciment, that ſhould knit them into one building with the Saints of God. As long as we are rotten with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in wee will rage without, and cry out of the moſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent for the breach of peace. Peace is lovely; but where there wants the true love of God and his truth: (that ſanctifieth the heart) there is no roome for true concord. The houſe of a wicked man ſaluted with peace repels it backe to him that offred it. <hi>Math.</hi> 10.13. He muſt be a ſonne of peace that will admit the ſalutati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Gods meſſengers, <hi>Luk.</hi> 10.6. <hi>Filius Eccleſiae,</hi> muſt be <hi>filius Dei.</hi> He that is a ſtranger to the Lords ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacle is moſt forward
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:1458:42"/>to diſjoynt the frame of it; and will prove in his mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters family that unruly ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant, that ſmites his fellow ſervants, and firſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaines of breach of peace. Oh let truth and peace kiſſe each other, and happy ſhall be the houſe of God. Let every man ſay with <hi>David Pſal.</hi> 120.7. I am for peace in Gods family, and curſed be they that are for warre.</p>
               <p>Secondly, we muſt learne from hence compaſſion and mutuall pitty, as being all of the ſame houſehold. In a body <hi>if one member ſuffer, all ſuffer with it;</hi> and the tongue will complaine of the little fingers ake. Let us commi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerate our brethren over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeas, and not ſuffer the ſeas
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:1458:43"/>more to devide us, than the wals of a houſe can devide a family. Thoſe cold winds that blow betweene us muſt no whit coole the fervor of our love; which wee muſt labour to keepe in heart, by our affections to them and prayers for them; every one labouring to expreſſe the forwardneſſe of his heart according as God offers abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity and meanes; for in this houſe Kings may doe that, which ſubjects cannot: the rich may doe that poore men are not able: men may doe what women are too weake to effect; But all may ſend prayers to heaven, like fire to fall upon the earth, and conſume their ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies.</p>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:1458:43"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Apoc.</hi> 8.5. The Lord Ieſus takes fire from the Altar, whereon our prayers are offred, and caſts it upon the earth: which preſently cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth <hi>voyces, thundrings, lighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings and an earthquake:</hi> that is, worketh our revenge, and our adverſaries ruine.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Revelat.</hi> 11. <hi>verſe</hi> 5. <hi>Out of their mouthes proceedeth fire;</hi> the prayers and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecies of the witneſſes devoureth their enemies. <hi>Act.</hi> 12. <hi>verſe</hi> 5. upon the Churches prayers <hi>Peter</hi> is delivered and bailed from priſon. <hi>Herods</hi> ſouldiers and chaines, the firſt and ſecond ward of keepers, doores and yron gates, are unable to deteine, when the forcible and fervent prayers of the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:1458:44"/>Church pull to heave him out. Oh pray, pray, pray for the peace of <hi>Zion;</hi> they ſhall proſper that thus love her. Never did the Church of God enjoy any great deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance, but prayer procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red it. If wee cannot pray, wee may not hope for any good to Gods people. Let us with <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Iohn</hi> at the howre of prayer, goe up to the temple, <hi>Act.</hi> 3.1. and likewiſe to the tops of our houſes, <hi>Act.</hi> 10.9. and both publikely and privately im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portune our Father, who ſeeth in ſecret as well as in the ſynagogue, to have mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy upon <hi>Zion.</hi> Hypocrites that pray onely in publike, have their rewardes (that they are not heard of God,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:1458:44"/>but ſeene of men) and do ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hinder than helpe in prayer; being an abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion unto the Lord. Yee that feare the Lord, both privately and publikely, make your requeſts knowne to him, that is ready to heare you: Take unto you words, and ſay, <hi>Spare thy peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple O Lord, and give not thine heritage to reproach, that the heathen ſhould rule over them &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Laſt-uſe in reſpect of ill neighbours.</head>
               <p>The laſt uſe is to ſhew us that the houſe of God hath alwaies beene peſtered with peeviſh, perverſe and perſecuting neighbours: lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle love hath beene lent to this houſe by ſinners, which
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:1458:45"/>are liberall enough in the hurt and hatred of it. Saints in a manner live by them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and are ſeldome kindly viſited by this un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind world. If heaven were not more propitious and bountifull, they of the houſehold of God were moſt miſerable. Warres on all ſides are waged againſt this houſe, and all cry <hi>downe with it, downe with it even to the ground.</hi> Rome ſeekes the ruine of it and runnes haſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to ſuch a prey; but wee are to know that all the warres of our adverſaries are ſacrilegious warres; as aſſaulting the very houſe of God. <hi>If any man deſtroy the temple of God, him will God deſtroy.</hi> What is more abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:1458:45"/>to God and man than to pull downe Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches? The holy warre of Rome is to ruinate Gods houſes, and reare up the houſes of <hi>Baal.</hi> Such holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe is helliſh; and though it proſper for a time; yet it returnes at laſt upon the hairy ſcalpe of ſuch as goe on to ſupplant his houſe, and cruſheth them under the ruines of their owne mine. <hi>Zech.</hi> 12.2.3, 6. the Church proveth at laſt <hi>a cup of poyſon,</hi> to eate out the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terals of theſe that devovre it: <hi>a burdenſome ſtone,</hi> to quaſh in peeces ſuch as lift at it: a <hi>hearth of fire</hi> to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume the droſſe and ſtubble that would choake and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:1458:46"/>
               <head>God judgeth his houſe.</head>
               <p>The people of God drink of the cup, <hi>Ie.</hi> 49.12. but not in judgement, that is, the judgement of perdition, 2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.7. Iudgement (ſaith the text) doth but begin with them: but where it endeth, it is a judgement in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed: God may bathe his ſword in the heaven of his Church, but it will come downe upon the People of his curſe to judgement, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 34.5.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>How the Lord judgeth his houſe.</head>
               <p>Iudgements fall upon this houſe either ſecretly or openly, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 12.14. Secret judgements are compared to the <hi>moth</hi> and <hi>rottenneſſe: I will be unto Ephraim as a
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:1458:46"/>moth, and to the houſe of Iudah as rottenneſſe, Tinea damum facit, non ſonitum.</hi> Thus God is ſooner found in the iſſue, than felt in the blow. A moth frets a garment ſecret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; and rottenneſſe eates into a tree unſenſibly. As a moth to a garment, and rot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenneſſe to a tree: ſo is God to the proceedings of <hi>Ephraim</hi> and deſignes of <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dah:</hi> that is, hee fruſtrateth their indeavours and makes their enterpriſes fruitleſſe. The pureſt garment is ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to the moth, and the ſtrongeſt tree to rottenneſſe: ſo the beſt and moſt wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy attempts may in their event and ſucceſſe, for the ſinnes of a nation, prove abortive and unprofitable:
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:1458:47"/>As may appeare in theſe five particulars: Firſt in <hi>wealth.</hi> Secondly, in <hi>ſtrength:</hi> Thirdly, in <hi>Counſels.</hi> Fourth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, in <hi>courage.</hi> Fiftly, in <hi>religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on:</hi> for in theſe eſpecially may wee obſerve the ſecret and moſt hidden judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of God.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>1. <hi>God is often a moth in our wealth and out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward eſtate.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Wealth is the bleſſing of God: yet <hi>Deut.</hi> 28, 16, 17, 18. a curſe is threatned a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it, and for diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence often executed: our ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyning, poſſeſſing, expen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of wealth, are often blaſted of God with ſecret judgements. When wee have ſecret waies to gather, God hath as ſecret wayes
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:1458:47"/>to ſcatter. <hi>Pro.</hi> 11.24. Wee learne of an ill maiſter, <hi>Matth.</hi> 4.3, rather to deſire to make ſtones bread, or raiſe a living out of lying &amp; other hard and unwarran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table courſes, than to make bread of Gods Word: wee thinke it neceſſary, that wee live, but how we care not: following the heathens rule, that wealth muſt bee gotten to ſupply neceſſity, no matter for right.
<note place="margin">Hor.</note> 
                  <hi>Vnde habeat nemo quaerit, ſed oportet habere.</hi> Theeves, Vſurers, oppreſſors, deceitfull Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants and tradeſmen are reſolved they muſt live, but how, in what manner, and by what meanes, they weigh not. O that wee would never force any ſtone
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:1458:48"/>to releive us: that every word of God might be our warrant, to take up whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever we owne or uſe; and we no more willing to ſin againſt God than not to live.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>2. <hi>God is often a moth in our ſtrength.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Strength of body is ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther bleſſing of God, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fitts a man to be ſerviceable to God and his countrey. The Church hath now need of able and hardy men, tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> may indure to ſtand in the open field, and fight for his truth. It is not our goods and lives that our enemies ſeeke for: it is our God and Religion that they thruſt at ſo to make roome for their owne. Oh how ſhould me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:1458:48"/>fit themſelves for this ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, and give over their drunken quarrels, veneries, and other effeminate cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, which have almoſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feebled our <hi>Engliſh</hi> nation, and diſabled our bodies to fight or brooke the open ayre. Iuſt it is with God to make us dye before our e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies that will not dye to theſe ſins, nor ſeeke to live according to the ancient diſcipline and example of our worthy progenitors, who have beene ranked with the beſt and ableſt ſoldiers in the world, when now being ſoaked in eaſe, and diſuſed to labour, wee are thruſt downe to the loweſt forme, and reputed of ſmall eſteeme amongſt
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:1458:49"/>our Neighbours.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>3. <hi>God is often a moth in our Counſels.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Counſell and wiſedome direct men to the fayreſt and moſt hopefull meanes of their ſecurity. Therefore to be ſmitten in the braine (<hi>Deut.</hi> 28.28. <hi>Zach.</hi> 12.4.) <hi>viz.</hi> either not to ſee the way, or in the event and iſſue of good Counſell not to proſper, is one of Gods ſoreſt judgements, and the trueſt forerunner of ruine. <hi>Our ſinnes</hi> (ſaith the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet) <hi>with-hold good things. Ier.</hi> 5.25. Even our beſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſultations are blaſted with the noyſome and peſtilent breath of our ſins. Oh that wee were ſenſible of this judgment, &amp; could mourne for it. Who ſeeth not in this,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:1458:49"/>this, Gods hand againſt us: &amp; yet (alas) how few lament it. We laugh at our Sorrowes, and lay nothing to heart. This is the way to make him that was a moth unto <hi>Ephraim,</hi> a moth unto us, to ſmite us even in our Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſells, and make them fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe in their hopefulleſt and beſt proceedings: and thus may God make the beſt of our Counſells &amp; conſultati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons rotten and moatheaten.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>4. <hi>God is often a moth in our courage.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>It was the high dignity of <hi>Ephraim</hi> to ſpeake with majeſtie in the midſt of all the tribes, and to cauſe trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling round about him. <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 13.1. <hi>But when he offered in Baal, he died.</hi> Sinne is the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:1458:50"/>dampe of courage, and the death of the heart, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cay of all excellency. And here wee finde God againe ſmiting, <hi>Deu.</hi> 28.28. <hi>Zach.</hi> 12.4. who as he takes away Counſell by blindneſſe and madneſſe, ſo doth hee take away courage by aſtoniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and amazement of heart.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>5. <hi>God is often a moth in our Religion.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Religion of all bleſſings is the greateſt, and yet in this we are often ſecretly ſmitten of God. This whole land hath great cauſe to prayſe God that the truth of the Goſpell is ſo publik<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly mainteined. This bleſſing we would learne to eſteeme, if wee were in the skins of
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:1458:50"/>our forefathers, or neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour brethren abroad. The time was when wee would gladly have ſerved God in Woods and Caves, and ſecret Cells: and how glad would our brethren abroad be, to ſee but one of our dayes: yet we enjoying full liberty of profeſſion &amp; pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe under good and whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome lawes, wee nothing anſwer Gods goodneſſe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to us, but live as if we wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted theſe ineſtimable pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges, and ſhew plainely the ſecret curſe of God up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on us. Errors and evills, ſuch as Poperie and Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie, may ſteale and creepe in at a poſterne gate: but (bleſſed be God) at an open and wide gate they finde no
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:1458:51"/>entrance. The ſword of au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority like the <hi>Cherubims,</hi> ſtands at the gates of our <hi>Eden</hi> to keepe out the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellious. Would God to our lawes, there were the like execution, and happie ſucceſſe in the meanes. The neglect in theſe, may cauſe God to bee a moth in the reſt, &amp; ſecretly to withhold from us the bleſſed influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of a Bleſſed Religion, and of our bliſſefull lawes. Thus much of Gods ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret judgements upon his houſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The more open and apparant judgements.</head>
               <p>Gods ſecret judgements conſiſt rather in the priva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of good things, than in the ſenſible ſmart of
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:1458:51"/>poſitive plagues. But when we are not apprehenſive of the moth, then he roares as a Lyon, teares and rends in peeces, takes away his prey, and ſuffers none to reſcue. When the good gifts of God want their bleſſing, when in our eſtates wee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come poore, in our bodies weake, and in our ſoules blind, fearefull and unholy; theſe wants ſhould ſtirre us up to ſeeke God: but if we like ſenſeleſſe people move not, God to make us more ſenſible, inflicts upon us ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer judgements, and makes us feele our loſſes in our lives, and our blowes in our bloud, and ſmites us as hee once ſmote the <hi>Philiſtims,</hi> firſt a farre of, in laying ſome
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:1458:52"/>
                  <hi>Dagon</hi> which we adore, flat on the ground: then ſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king off hands and head, (wherein wee truſt for helpe) he leaves it an uſeles ſtumpe. When blockiſh men regard not this, The Lord drawes nearer, and ſmites their bodies with ſharpe paynes, and yet proceeding farther, he take away their lives with the ſword. Eaſy warnings neglected, end in greater woes, &amp; God that at firſt would faine be heard, at laſt will worke his plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, and will not heare. <hi>Ezoc.</hi> 14.21. tells us of foure ſore judgements, the <hi>Sword, Famine, Peſtilence,</hi> and <hi>noy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome Beaſts.</hi> Some of theſe have raged in this Land, and wee may feare the reſt will
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:1458:52"/>follow, unleſſe we prevent them by our repentance. The Lyon hath rored: who will not feare? The Lord God hath ſpoken, who can but prophecie?</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>God in judging his houſe makes choyce of a fit time.</head>
               <p>The originall word <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> imployeth rather the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venience of ſeaſon, than the continuance of time. As God knoweth when to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver his, ſo he hath his ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon wherein to puniſh and chaſtize them: and that firſt, <hi>to revenge the quarrell of his covenant, Lev.</hi> 26.25. It is ill conteſting with God, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially for them that are linked in covenant with him. <hi>You have I knowne of all
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:1458:53"/>the families of the earth: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I will puniſh you for all your iniquities, Amo.</hi> 3.2. Secondly in reſpect of the Goſpell, which cannot bee preached without oppoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of outward violence, <hi>Matth.</hi> 11.12. <hi>Luk.</hi> 16.16, violent men will prey upon Gods kingdome, and every wicked man will have a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blow at it. Like Kites upon a Carkeiſe ſo are Gods ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies upon his Church, <hi>Luke</hi> 17.37. Thirdly, this ſeaſon here poynted at, ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fills the prophecie of Chriſt, <hi>Matth.</hi> 24.9. For here <hi>Peter</hi> writing to the diſperſed <hi>Iewes,</hi> five yeares before the deſtruction of <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> tells them that now is the time to deliver them up to
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:1458:53"/>be afflicted, killed, and hated as his maſter Chriſt foretold before his death. Fourthly, Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s are too great ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers in their afflictions, as in an eſtate unwonted: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Peter</hi> bringeth this rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to bring Chriſtians to themſelves, <hi>for the time is come, &amp;c.</hi> that is, God hath ſent you the fitteſt ſeaſon of your tryall: and therefore <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> be not ſtrangers in things familiar and ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable, and wherein you ought to bee the beſt ſtudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. Fiftly, the ſeaſon bids you expect the harveſt: <hi>you ſow in teares, and ſhall reape in joy:</hi> When others that ſowe in joy, ſhall reape in ſorrow. <hi>Philip.</hi> 1.28. 2. <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 1.6.7. Little doe the Iewes know
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:1458:54"/>their approching miſeries; their perdition haſtneth, and you ſhall be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forted when you ſee Chriſt as good as his word. Vpon this ground I verily beleeve is that to the <hi>Hebrewes, Heb.</hi> 10.36, 37. <hi>Yet a little while, and hee that ſhall come will come, and will not tarry.</hi> You have a promiſe that Chriſt will come upon the unbeleeving Iewes and deſtroy them: bee you patient and waite: live by faith: and the Lord will come and ſave you, when that diſobedient na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion periſheth. <hi>Iames</hi> 5.1. <hi>Goe to now ye rich Iewes, weepe and houle, &amp;c.</hi> The Apoſtle fetcheth his reaſon from their laſt dayes and miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries neere at hand, that is,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:1458:54"/>the very periode of your kingdome and policye is now approching, &amp;c. It ſhall bee a comfort to us to ſee the downefall of <hi>Rome</hi> according to holy prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, as it was to the belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Iewes to ſee Chriſts promiſe fulfilled upon <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem;</hi> hee had threatned and in time executed his decree in puniſhing the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Vſe</hi> 1. To teach us that afflictions ſhould not bee ſtrange to the godly, that live at home in their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers familie, and make his word their ſtay. For what can be ſtrange that falls out ſeaſonably? Yee and Snow in winter, thunder and ligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tening in Sommer, are no
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:1458:55"/>wonders: no more can af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions ſeeme ſtrange, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing they are alwayes fitted to their owne proper time.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Vſe</hi> 2. Afflictions are not dangerous nor hurtfull; (howſoever ſharpe and bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter) becauſe ſeaſonable. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny a thing is undone, by miſſing its owne ſeaſon. If ſowen corne be not buried with winter ſnow, and nip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped with froſts (whereby wormes and weedes are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed) it will not flouriſh afterward, no not in the ſtrength of Sommer. The want of ſeaſonable correcti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on hazardeth many a ſoule, &amp; thouſands periſh, becauſe they know not even this their acceptable time. But thoſe happie croſſes that
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:1458:55"/>fall ſeaſonably upon us, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver departe without a bleſſing. This makes a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians chaines to bee chaines of gold, and the markes of the Lord Ieſus to be glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Vſe</hi> 3. Afflictions are glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious and beautifull in the eyes of the Lord. <hi>Every thing</hi> (ſaith the wiſe man) <hi>is comely in his ſeaſon:</hi> then it flouriſheth and floureth, and expreſſeth beauty to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very beholder. The ſcars of a ſouldier received in the field are enſignes of valour: and the wounds which a Chriſtian ſuffereth in figh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the good fight, are im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions of honour.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Vſe</hi> 4. Afflictions are pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable; time and ſeaſon make
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:1458:56"/>for the good of all things. The poore woman of <hi>Edeſſa</hi> fearing to come too late to ſuffer with Chriſtians, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gets her ſelfe, and with her child in her arines, and her clothes halfe on, meets the Deputy in the face, and fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red not to tell him the cauſe of he haſte, to wit, leaſt he ſhould have made an end before her comming; who deſired as well to dye, as to live with Chriſtians.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Vſe</hi> 5. Afflictions are changeable. No ſeaſon will laſt alwayes, there will bee an end of the Saints ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings, the rod ſhall not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes reſt upon them, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 125.3. God knowes how to take off, and lay on his owne blowes, how to bring in
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:1458:56"/>and bring out his owne ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons. Sommer it ſelfe would bee teadious if Winter ſhould not follow it out, and bring it in. Afflictions ſhould never have an after fruite; were they ever grevious for the preſent, and had no change. They are but an exerciſe, which without change cannot bee endured.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>God having a fit time, doth but begin with his houſe.</head>
               <p>In theſe words is expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the meaſure and method of afflictions; the beleeving Iewes have the firſt hanſell. Their ſhare is the firſt and leaſt, but not the laſt of the cup, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 75.6. The beſt of good, and the worſt of ill, doth alwayes ſettle to the
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:1458:57"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:1458:57"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="42" facs="tcp:1458:58"/>bottome. Hence it is that wicked men ſip of the cup of pleaſure before the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: but the godly taſt of the cup of ſorrow before the wicked: <hi>Iſa.</hi> 49.12.34.5. <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.9. Heaven firſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dures the ſword, then the earth, <hi>Ier.</hi> 25.17, 18, 19. <hi>All Nations, Egypt, and the min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gled people,</hi> muſt pledge in that cup, wherein <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> begins. Every ſoule muſt ſmart for ſinne, but the <hi>Iew</hi> firſt, and then the <hi>Gentile, Rom.</hi> 2.9.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 1. Learne Gods ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity that will not ſpare ſinne in his owne, no not when he ſpares it in a wicked man. A maiſter of a family will often winke at the misbeha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour of ſtangers, but will
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:1458:58"/>not ſuffer his children to looke awry.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Vſe</hi> 2. See Gods mercy; that having tempered the bitter cup of his wrath, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poynts his owne to taſt the top, reſerving all the dregs for the wicked; who muſt wring them out; whiles his owne ſervants do but waſh their lips, and let downe ſome drops, to know how bitter ſin is in the bad fruites of it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Vſe</hi> 3. This helps to plead the cauſe of Gods houſe againſt the enemies thereof; Papiſts vpbraide Proteſtants with their calamities, as a curſe upon their cauſe; af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firming that our Churches (if true) would flouriſh, and appeare by thoſe viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:1458:59"/>ſignes which accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny the glorious monarchy of the Catholick Church. But ſtay there; Romaniſts reckon without their hoſt, and take an intruder for the maiſter of the houſe. Their holy father hath played the falſe Prophet, and healed the wound of the Romane Monarchy with a plaiſter of new Idolatry, ſo that <hi>all the world wondereth</hi> after him, <hi>Rev.</hi> 13.3. No marvaile then, if their Church flouriſh, having ſuch a wicked throng to defend it; whoſe portion is the botome of the cup in Gods hand: and therefore in order of time the laſt <hi>Bohemia,</hi> the <hi>Palati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, Churches of Germany</hi> and <hi>France,</hi> have drunke and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:1458:59"/>to others; yet never the leſſe pretious in Gods eye, becauſe the firſt in trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. Let others expect that time when the Lord Ieſus ſhall arme himſelfe with that power, which as yet ſtirs not, and reigne not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in his owne, but over his enemies, by making them angry; when the time of his wrath commeth, to recompence his ſervants for their ſufferings, and ſinners for their wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; That the one may glory in the perfection of their bleſſedneſſe, and the other pine under the preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of their miſeries. They that now deſtroy the earth, muſt themſelves be deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.17.18. The times
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:1458:60"/>for perſecution, ratified by an oath, <hi>Dan.</hi> 12.7. are by the oath of the ſame Angel proclaymed to continue no longer, <hi>Rev.</hi> 10.6. The con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance of Antichriſts ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cesfull tyranny is the leſſe to be admired, ſeeing Chriſt hath ſworne, that the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane monarchy in the ten hornes, ſhall enjoy ſo long a terme to doe miſcheife both to the naturall few, and to the ſurrogate Iſrael of God, <hi>Luk.</hi> 22.24. <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.2. But when the <hi>time, times</hi> and <hi>halfe a time</hi> ſhall be no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, and the oath of the 42. moneths ſhall expire: then the latter end of Antichriſt ſhall be worſe than his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning. Pleade therefore the cauſe of Gods people,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:1458:60"/>and let the world take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice, that theſe judgements begun in the Church, will end in her enemies.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Vſe</hi> 4. Let every Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an learne hence to plead his owne cauſe, and not to caſt away his confidence in the evill houre of tentation; for the Devill will put hard to perſwade him, that hee is in worſe caſe than other men, and more hated of God becauſe his hand is heavier upon him. But know, that in chaſtiſements, God be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins with his beſt ſervants; who therefore muſt take it as an argument of his love.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Sinners Sorrow.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Where God begins to judge,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:1458:61"/>hee makes not there an end.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The end of Iudgement is wofull; and the laſt laſh of Gods ſcourge workes the bittereſt ſmart. In the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedient or rebellious here mentioned, wee have a ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible patterne for ungodly men. The Iewes wiſhed the blood of Chriſt to be upon them and their children. Reade but their end in ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and it will ſuffice to move a heart of flint, and make us compaſſionate to deſperate ſinners. Beſides, this their end was eternall perdition: for that is the end of ungodly men diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beying the Goſpel. It is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in ſtory, that when the Romans had ſlaine a great number of them upon the
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:1458:61"/>bankes of <hi>Iordan,</hi> and tum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled their carkeiſes into the river, they never left ſwimming till they fell into the lake of <hi>Sodom,</hi> where they were buried as in a grave: a tipe of the ſinking of their ſoules, into the gulfe of hell; for S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Iohn</hi> living to ſee their miſerable end, turnes the ſtile of hell, and tearmes it the lake of fire and brimſtone, <hi>Rev.</hi> 19.20. where I beleeve that he al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ludes to this fearefull pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage of the Iewes eternall perdition. The better to conceive of the end menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned in the text, let us con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult with our Saviour, who by the end underſtands the deſtruction of <hi>Ieruſalem. Matth.</hi> 24.6.13.14. <hi>The end
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:1458:62"/>is not yet:</hi> that is, with the firſt ſignes foregoing <hi>Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalems</hi> deſtruction. <hi>He that endures to the end ſhall be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, i.e.</hi> he that houlds out in other ſignes of perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſcandall, apoſtacy, ſhall bee ſaved even temporally when the end of <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> is come; as all the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans were; being warned by a voyce from heaven to remoove to <hi>Pella. Then ſhall the end come:</hi> that is, no ſoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner ſhall the Goſpell bee preached to the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> and the <hi>Iewes</hi> rejected, but the <hi>Romane</hi> Army ſhall come and deſtroy <hi>Ieruſalem, Dan.</hi> 9.26. Meſſiah being once cut off from the <hi>Iewes,</hi> they ſhall no longer bee his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, but another that he will
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:1458:62"/>chooſe ſhall come, and ſpread over them the wing of abomination: Notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding with many ſhall he confirme his covenant, and by ſeaven yeares labour ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a Church amongſt the <hi>Iewes,</hi> which hee will ſave, when hee ſuffers the reſt to periſh. This is likewiſe the end which <hi>Peter</hi> mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, verſ. 7. before the text; by conſideration whereof, he exhorteth the Chriſtian <hi>Iewes</hi> to ſobriety, watchful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and prayer. <hi>Iohn</hi> out li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving this Apoſtle, points it out by an houre, 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 2.18.</p>
               <p>This example of the end of the <hi>Iewiſh</hi> Nation, muſt become a rule to all Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, to take heed of rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:1458:63"/>againſt the Goſpell: God that ſpared not the <hi>Iewes,</hi> will ſpare none, that long provoke his patience. And here let us obſerve foure things.</p>
               <p n="1">1. All the wicked muſt have an end; and that firſt, of Gods patience: 2. of their pleaſures: 3. of their lives. God will not alwaies beare the reproaches of ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, neither ſhall they al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes injoy their pleaſures, which at the beſt are but pleaſures of ſinne for a ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; and with their naturall lives all their jollities in this world come to their peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>od.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The end of the wicked is miſerable; for when it commeth it laſteth and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinueth;
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:1458:63"/>one miſery over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taketh an other, they muſt <hi>drinke, and be drunke, and ſpue, and fall, and riſe no more; Ier.</hi> 25.27. Neither can they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe to drinke, becauſe Gods people have drunke before them; And if they drinke whoſe ſinnes are pardoned, then ſuch as have no par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, muſt needs have judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment endleſſe, eaſeleſſe, and remedileſſe. Now the miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of this end of the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked conſiſts, 1. In the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamity of it; hence com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared to <hi>unquenchable fire, utter darkeneſſe, the never dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing worme, and everlaſting perdition.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. In the place, called hell, a priſon, <hi>tartarus, gehenna,</hi> and bottomleſſe pit. Hell is
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:1458:64"/>beneath all comfort: a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is a ſtreight cuſtody of the ſoule; <hi>tartarus</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, a place of horror and feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſpectacles: <hi>Gehenna,</hi> a vally, where Idolaters burnt their children with fire, and to prevent all pitty, drum<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> were beaten up, to drowne the horrible hideous cryes of Infants. No pitty in hell, for all the yelling of dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned ſpirits: a bottomleſſe pit, out of which the dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned ſhall never bee able to creepe or craule.</p>
               <p n="3">3. In their lamentation, they ſhall weepe their bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies full, and bee never the better. To weeping they ſhall adde wailing &amp; wrin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging of hands: and the height of their lamentation
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:1458:64"/>ſhall be gnaſhing of teeth. Their teeth ſhall chatter, as if extremity of cold chilled them: much weeping cools the heart, daunts the ſpirits, and ſets the whole body in a ſhaking. Such cooling ſhal the wicked finde in the hot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt fire.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Though the damned feele exquiſite torments, yet they ſhall never know their full extremity. <hi>Peter</hi> ſtands amazed in expreſſing their end, and ſmothers the ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour under a queſtion, as un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>utterable: <hi>What ſhall the end be?</hi> Good men can fathom the depth of their ſoreſt ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamities, and <hi>Peter</hi> here de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termines their croſſes with a beginning; but when hee commeth to decipher the
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:1458:65"/>end of the wicked, as being at a <hi>non plus</hi> hee ſtops the currant of his diſcourſe and conceales the reſt under a cloud of admiration. A wicked mans end is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowne, from the capacity of the ſubject: he ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver know, what his ſtrength is able to beare. He might count himſelfe happy, if hee were as a ſtone in a rocke of flint, which as it taſteth no joy, ſo feeles no paine. 2. It is not to bee expreſſed for the extremity of the tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; So that a wicked man ſhall never know his worſt. 3. It cannot be knowne for the perpetuity of it, whence wee may ſay of their tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, as of the joyes of heaven: The eye of man ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:1458:65"/>ſaw them, yea, ſuch as the eare hath not heard; nor (which ſurpaſſeth the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt ſtraine) they never en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred into the heart of man; which of all things created, approacheth neereſt to an infinite nature.</p>
               <p n="4">4. That which ſhall bee knowne, ſhall be enough to cruſh and confound every wicked ſinner. He ſhall not know where to appeare or hide his head. Happy man, if the mountaines would overlay, and the rocks cruſh him in pieces: no burthen would then be too heavy, no waight or preſſure too painefull, no puniſhment too great, that would ſhelter him from the piercing eye and revenging ſtroke of his
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:1458:66"/>angry judge. Alaſſe, how can men living conteſt with the Almighty, outface his word, outbrave his juſtice? who when they are dead, cannot brooke the frowne of his countenance, nor put to ſilence the voyce of deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paire. I ſhould now con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude this point with the counſell of Chriſt, <hi>Math.</hi> 5.25. <hi>Agree with thy adverſary quickely, whilſt thou art in the way, leaſt at any time,</hi> (for thou knoweſt not when thy appearance ſhall be) <hi>he deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver thee to the Iudge, the Iudge to the laylor, the laylor to the priſon,</hi> where thou muſt lye for ever.</p>
               <p>But in the cloſe of this verſe and that which fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth, mention is made of
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:1458:66"/>the true cauſe of all this mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery, &amp; that is eſpecially the diſobedience of the Goſpel. The Law is added as a light of former ſinnes, conſiſting of impiety againſt God, and cruelty againſt man. The <hi>Iewes</hi> crucified Chriſt, a le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall ſinne, but they crucified themſelves in rejecting his bloud, and the Goſpell that offered them pardon for that ſinne and all others. The fault was foule enough to murther Chriſt, but to murther their ſoules in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nying ſalvation by his blood, was of all ſinnes the greateſt. They are branded for ungodly perſons by the teſtimony of the Law, and their owne wicked actions, of Idolatrie and obſtinacy.
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:1458:67"/>They are ſinners deepe ſey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed in ſingular bloodſhed and butchery of Chriſt and his Saints: but the tranſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent ſinne is here fairely characterized by a ſpeciall act, and by a ſpeciall object. The act is Evangelicall diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedience; and the object, the Goſpell it ſelfe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Goſpell.</head>
               <p>In giving the Goſpell to a Nation, it is more than he does to all Nations: where the Goſpell is given, faith and obedience are but given to ſome in that Nation. The Goſpell diſtinguiſheth Nations; faith and the gift thereof, the men that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe it. Grace is given where it is not received. Given to a Nation, of which
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:1458:67"/>it may more eaſily bee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected than embraced. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 147.19, 20. here the Word is not revealed alike to all. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 81.11. here rejected by them to whom it was given. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.70. <hi>Davids</hi> heart being pined with want, takes pleaſure in the Word; others having their hearts fat and greaſie, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe it. <hi>Iſai.</hi> 6.9, 10. Men have hearts too fatte to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve, eares too heavy to heare, and eyes cloſed up from ſeeing. The Goſpell is as ſtrange to ſome that heare it, as thoſe that never heard it, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 8.12. Chriſt came to his owne, and yet was not owned by them, <hi>Iohn</hi> 1.11. Some received him, verſ. 12. when the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:1458:68"/>rejected him. Theſe 1. had <hi>power to beleeve.</hi> 2. <hi>to receive.</hi> 3. <hi>to be ſonnes.</hi> In the myſteries of the Goſpell, prudent men come ſhort of Infants, <hi>Luke</hi> 10.12. and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive in parrables, what o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers receive in power, <hi>Luke</hi> 8.10. yea, finde that ſavour <hi>death unto death,</hi> which to others is <hi>life unto life,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.15, 16.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Gods free Grace.</head>
               <p>Shall wee ſay this is the worke of our owne wils, and the good uſe of our owne freedome? This were to render more than wee receive, and to glory in our owne power and praiſe. Thus to differ were to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace the Goſpell, that grants unto us deliverance
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:1458:68"/>from enemies, and obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence unto friends, <hi>Luke</hi> 1.74. Our good friends in heaven mutually conſpired our victory and obedience. God the Father, Sonne, and holy Ghoſt, bound not up the hands of our enemies, but gave us alſo hearts to obey for this gift.</p>
               <p>1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.7. preſſeth upon the pride of us all, <hi>Phyſical<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, Politically, Theologically.</hi> Who made man, or man to differ from a beaſt? He were a beaſt, that would not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge God for the Author of both: Who rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth man to honour or di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction of civill order? Surely the ſame God that made him preferres him. But above all, grace is leaſt
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:1458:69"/>in our command, and moſt in the power of God; nay, wholly from him, as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peares by the <hi>gift of faith,</hi> a new principle, nature never acknowledged; <hi>by righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,</hi> a purchaſe, that never came out of our vertues; <hi>by holyneſſe,</hi> a worke, not of our wils, but the ſanctifying Spirit.</p>
               <p>Faith is a firme principle of the Goſpell, and keepes us by the power of God, and not our owne, unto ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.5. I know what advantage is taken, <hi>Ier.</hi> 32.40. by turning the text from <hi>They ſhall not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part,</hi> into <hi>They may not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part.</hi> Loath the words ſhould be more peremptory than poſſible. <hi>Poſſible</hi> they
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:1458:69"/>would have it runne, and then raiſe their anſwer a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Gods grace, that faith or feare is not ſo cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainely placed in the heart; but as it may ſtay, ſo depart, if wee will forward either. God puts in our hearts a new principle, and that for this end, that we might bee aſſured of the new Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, and of our cleaving to God; and therefore fuller aſſurance than of a poſſibili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and power in our ſelves. The Legall and Evangelicall principles of well living, (as we ſhall afterwards de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare) differ much in nature, office, and end. God by ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginall righteouſneſſe left man to the tryall of his owne power. But by Faith
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:1458:70"/>or the new principle, hath caſt man upon himſelfe, and a holy and happy depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dencie upon his power for ſalvation: The Goſpel is his beſt law for life, and ſureſt power of God, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.16, to ſave him; yet with this caution, that wee beleeve. Promiſes are generall, and muſt bee received as they are propounded; Faith makes them particular to us, and in our deeds and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terminations wee may pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume no further than the generall evidence applied; we muſt ſilence all ſearch of further ſecrets, and Gods will revealed muſt bee our rule, and to reach higher by his decrees, is to outreach our ſelves and rove about the truth.</p>
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:1458:70"/>
               <p>If any ſay, why have ſome the Goſpel and not Faith? I ſilence his preſumption with Gods freedome, and ſay, why hath hee either? His Goſpell is a pledge of his love, and thy faith of his favour, thou haſt no wrong whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he counts thee worthy of neither. If he have a liſt to leave thee an Infidel, thou art but thy ſelfe. His Law containes wonders, and workes them daily in prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching. All heare the ſame word, yet have not the ſame affection. Hee ſpeakes too boldly of Gods coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels, that will reaſon by our diſpoſitions. <hi>O the depth of the riches, both of the wiſedome and wayes of God! His judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments muſt bee paſt</hi> our fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding,
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:1458:71"/>and fadoming: Wee muſt feare to ſearch too much, and take heed of an evill eye, becauſe his is good. Hee cals and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands by his word, and of them he chooſeth as few or many as hee pleaſeth. Hee makes ſome laſt in Vocati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, firſt in Election, &amp; ſome he cals firſt that hee never chooſeth. The <hi>Iewes</hi> by <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> in my text are divided, and the nation differenced in receiving and rejecting the Goſpell.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>70. <hi>Famous yeeres.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Foure things would fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther bee unfolded: 1. the time of this end. 2. the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons. 3. the judgement. 4. the cauſe. The time is the laſt yeere, or at leaſt the laſt
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:1458:71"/>weeke of the 70. weekes of <hi>Daniel, Dan.</hi> 9.24, The <hi>Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles, Luke</hi> 21.24, have <hi>times to fulfill,</hi> and from former times they come to latter times, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.1. which di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide themſelves, <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.25. &amp; 12.7. <hi>Rev.</hi> 12.14. into <hi>a time, times, and halfe a time.</hi> So the <hi>Iewes</hi> have the like account and computation, and falling upon their laſt times, have them by <hi>Daniel</hi> determined in the number of 70. weekes. Theſe make ſeaven points or periods of their time, every period containing 70. yeares, and ſix of them are to bee held for the expectation of the Meſſiah: The ſeaventh is the moſt famous and illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrious of all the reſt. Firſt,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:1458:72"/>for the incarnation of our Saviour. 2. For his doctrine and death. 3. For <hi>Ieruſalems</hi> deſolation and deſtruction, which is the end wee have now in hand. 70. yeeres take up this time; the firſt yeere begins with Chriſts birth and bleſſed comming into the world, and for 30. yeeres, <hi>Luke</hi> 3.23. he lives in obſcurity, ſave his diſputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion with the Doctors at his age of 12. yeeres: 18. yeeres more he ſpends in la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour and ſubjection to his parents. This time puts well on the 70. yeeres, and for one weeke, counting from 30. to 38. is Chriſt moſt fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous in publiſhing him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe Meſſiah, <hi>Dan.</hi> 9.27. and for 7. yeeres confirmes the
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:1458:72"/>covenant with many. Hee preacheth by himſelfe for halfe of this weeke, he dies in the middſt of it, and char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth his Apoſtles to conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue the reſt and remainder of it to the <hi>Iewes</hi> onely.</p>
               <p>A wonderfull mercy to this nation, if there had beene any good nature in it: never man ſpake like him, did like him, or ſuffered like him. He will neither off the Croſſe, nor out of the Pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit, till hee have accompli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed a weeke of extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary mercy to an ill deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving nation: but this weeke ended, in the 38. yeere of his incarnation, hee comes to <hi>Peter</hi> in a voyce and viſion, to perſwade him hee may freely preach and converſe
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:1458:73"/>with the <hi>Gentiles, Act.</hi> 10. <hi>Paul</hi> takes this for another argument of mercy in the beginning of judgement. <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.14. He provokes to emulation and ſalvation by the <hi>Gentiles;</hi> and thus conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued the Goſpell betweene <hi>Iew</hi> and <hi>Gentile</hi> a long time: But this obſtinate people would bee moved by no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, and therefore in the laſt weeke, if not the laſt yeere, are deſtroyed.</p>
               <p>The deſolator Chriſt, or the <hi>Romanes,</hi> (it mattereth not,) now executeth the words of him that in the daies of his fleſh uttered them, <hi>Math.</hi> 22.7. Chriſt <hi>the King ſendeth forth his armies, and deſtroies the murtherers, and burnes their Citie.</hi> I have
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:1458:73"/>received it from the Oracle of God, and learned Expoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, M. <hi>Ioſeph Meade,</hi> the beſt Delian diver that ever I found in theſe myſteries; that S. <hi>Iames</hi> Chap. 5.7, 8. meanes by the comming of Chriſt, his comming in the <hi>Romane</hi> army: So <hi>Zachary</hi> hath it, <hi>Zach.</hi> 14.4. his feete in the <hi>Romanes</hi> ſtand upon the ſame mount he prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cied; and this wary Expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitor takes further warrant from an Ancient Writer, and alleageth <hi>Oecumenius</hi> ſo clearing the text before him.</p>
               <p>Brethren, the Bible is the beſt Hiſtory in the world; it triumpheth over all hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane knowledge, and carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth our minds and memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:1458:74"/>over the vaſt and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring ſpace of time, not onely paſt, but yet to come. It makes us live now, as if we had lived with our dead Anceſtors, or were to live with our ſurviving poſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. It gives us piercing eies, &amp; makes us ſee into the very deepth of darkeneſſe, and to foretell deeds that are yet to be done.</p>
               <p>Onely much wiſedome, and much watchfulneſſe are required of him that will apply for good ſuch ſecrets. The pure oyle, <hi>Exod.</hi> 27.20. for the lights to cauſe the lamps to burne, muſt bee beaten; for with much la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour and affliction the light of Gods word muſt bee prepared, and with patience
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:1458:74"/>preached, and made to ſhine in the Church. Would God this nationall example of the <hi>Iewes,</hi> might bee the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of our nation: we have had better than a 70, yeeres continuance of the glorious Goſpell; if we pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voke God like theſe ſtub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borne <hi>Iewes,</hi> it is our duty from the like danger to looke for the like puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. I will ſay no more, I ſee the patience and puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the ſame God: take him whilſt he offereth mercy, leaſt hee leave thee, when thou would bee glad to finde his favour.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The perſons.</head>
               <p>The perſons here puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, are the <hi>Iewes,</hi> and muſt be an example unto us, of ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinacy
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:1458:75"/>and wilfulneſſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God. They are bold to ſinne, and muſt beare with baſeneſſe the marke of God above all people.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Their end and miſery.</head>
               <p>Their end is the very tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gedie of all miſeries, and compendium of the laſt woe. They are puniſhed as if doomeſday were come upon them. God it is that will bee the Author of all tragedies, and write out all men the parts they are to play in this world. Hee is not partiall to the greateſt, when they grow inſolent a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him. <hi>Darius</hi> of a great Emperour is put to play the poore begger, and in the drought of death to call for drinke from an ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie.
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:1458:75"/>
                  <hi>Baiazet</hi> the grand Sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nior of the <hi>Turkes,</hi> turnes the ſtage of his honour, into a footſtoole for <hi>Tamberlane</hi> to mount on horſe-backe. <hi>Valerian,</hi> by <hi>Sapores</hi> is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded the ſame ſervice, and thouſands more of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples might bee brought. The greateſt Worthy, and the leaſt worme are ſubjects to God, and without wrong, muſt bee made to ſerve his providence. For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune (wee ſay) on the great Theater of the world deales with us, as wee doe with our ſelves in the change of our garments in our leſſer Chambers: when we have unclad our ſelves, every man weareth but his owne skin: and ſo the proudeſt, and
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:1458:76"/>moſt preſumptuous are of the ſame nature with the meaneſt, when they are ſtripped of ſome few raggs they weare: wee are to meete with an hard maſter, that will not pardon us far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>things, <hi>Math.</hi> 5.26.</p>
               <p>In the way we might have done well, but now being come to the end of our journey, we muſt abide both our pay and paine. Hell fire will be the hotter, by how much God in patience hath beene the cooler: <hi>Tarditas ſupplicij gravitate penſatur,</hi> the calme of Gods mercy, ends in the tempeſt of his juſtice. Men ſhall ſee now how to ſorrow, but not to ſolace themſelves. <hi>Iſid. l.</hi> 1. <hi>de ſum. bon. Ad aggrevatum
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:1458:76"/>ut videant unde doleant, non ad conſolationem, ut videant unde gandeant,</hi> they have played with thoſe things that now will not pleaſe them. When they come to number with God as well for magnitude as multitude of ſinnes, they ſhall perceive themſelves burthened as wel for conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence as memory. There is ſinne (ſaith a Father) both in weight and number, <hi>etſi non timeas quando expendis, time quando numeras.</hi> The many ſeventies injoyed by the <hi>Iewes,</hi> became ſevere in the count, and for ſhort weekes they have now ſharpe miſeries. <hi>Cum illis ludunt quae illis laedunt,</hi> They ſport with that which will not ſpare them. They be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:1458:77"/>careleſſe of their e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils, and then careleſſeneſſe, ſadneſſe &amp; ſuddenneſſe will overtake them. The time was when God called for that, which they would not give, and now may call for that which God will not grant; like <hi>Dives</hi> they deny morſels, and want dropps when they neede them. Would they give their ſoules to God, when they have given them to the devils, he will none of them but commands (as the text hath it) the devils to fetch them without their wils. It is ſmall happineſſe that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes with ſo heavy newes. Some ſay <hi>he is a happy ſonne whoſe father goes to the devill:</hi> but an heire of ſuch
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:1458:77"/>happineſſe may have as hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy an end. <hi>Abraham</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred <hi>Dives</hi> of paines in hell for pleaſures upon earth.</p>
               <p>Men that have deſpiſed the Goſpell were bleſſed, if they might die like beaſts, and be buried like wormes. A Toad is touched with leſſe miſery in the hatred of man, than men that for ſinne are hated of God. A bitter cup that is in Gods keeping, and though ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance bee not powred out of it, yet it neither ſleepeth, nor reſteth there for ever. Iudgements doe not follow crimes as thunder doth lightning, neither is a wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked mans pang alwayes ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſcribed in his forehead.
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:1458:78"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="81" facs="tcp:1458:78"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="82" facs="tcp:1458:79"/>Wickedneſſe hath Sugar in the mouth and ſorrow in the heart; wantonneſſe like oyle ſhineth in the face, and is feſtered in the ſoule: worldly things upon the beſt termes are vaine, but vile with ſinne: men may up and be rich with injury, grow great by ſecret evils, and not know their wofull end. If theſe things had better conditions they were no great friends to us, but as they are by us to cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted, they are no leſſe then tormenters. A gay coate will not alwayes beare out a corrupt heart, nor high title a hell in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sophar</hi> in the booke of <hi>Iob</hi> powreth out curſes up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:1458:79"/>the head of an impious man, te les him hee ſhall ſucke the gall of Aſpes and be ſlaine by a Vipers tongue. The ſunne that ſhineth faire ſix dayes upon a wicked mans tabernacle, may bee clouded the ſeventh, and then for delay he comes to pay the intereſt. Surely when the heavens ſhall ſhrivell as a ſcrole, and the Mountaines move like frighted men, then no Cave ſhall bee found to receive, or mighty Mountaines to fall upon them. Count them miſerable who for a while are made fortunate by im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piety, fooles are at no time happy: if wicked men were wiſe they would ceaſe to be evill. Iniquity is an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:1458:80"/>proofe, both of fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and miſery. Grieve not at the ſinners impunitie and proſperity, becauſe rightly diſcerned they even then neither proſper or goe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puniſhed.</p>
               <p>Vulgar people for their names lie buried with their bodies: but great perſons and kingdomes ſtand upon record. We are marveilous blind in their uſe, men thinke ſuch and ſuch per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons miſcarried not by ſin, but ſimplicity. They are dare hazzard the ſame way, and looke for better ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe. Let mee never bee credited if they fare bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then their neighbours. Their Chronicles wil come out with the ſame edition
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:1458:80"/>and addition of better wits. It is no working againſt Gods workes that hath al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes curſed ill courſes: mans end in this world, ends not his miſery in hell. Hee ſtands for a time upon the ſlippcrie yee, and being in darkeneſſe knowes not when Gods Angell ſhall puſh him into hell, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 35.6. Three aggravations of his miſery, firſt, the place of his ſtanding, this is ſlipperie. Secondly, it is poſſeſſed with darkeneſſe, and therefore being in the way to fall, hee cannot have the wit to place one foote for ſafety. Hee that walkes upon the yee in darkeneſſe muſt needs have a downefall as deadly, as a break-neck.</p>
               <pb n="86" facs="tcp:1458:81"/>
               <p>God is angry every day with ſinners, and could find in his heart to caſt them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to hell, that he ſpares them is his patience not his par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, for hee will puniſh in the end. Hee will one day breath fire upon thoſe coles that in mercy hee breathed into us. His fire ſhall fall as raine, catch them like ſnares. To ſire he will adde brimſtone, and to both an horrible tempeſt, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 11.6. The ſtreame and cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent of Gods wrath ſhall runne like a River of brim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone, the very pile of the pit is fire, and that fire hath alſo much wood to worke on, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 30.33. This after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clap of hell is the worſt, and ſhould have our greateſt
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:1458:81"/>care of prevention before it be too late, and wee have loſt both our lives and him that is unto us both life and length of daies.</p>
               <p>One hand by the pulſe askes the other how wee doe, and our eye is on our Vrine to divine in what danger wee are: why is there not a pulſe panting and beating within to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſh us of our inward eſtate? With what preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion doe we daily provoke God to blow theſe Soules into hell that once he brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed into our bodies? The Lord teach us Wiſedome to thinke of our end, that when wee are taken of our feete to fall on our beds, and from them to the cold
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:1458:82"/>earth, we may not be raiſed off our foundation, but reſt on him that will ſuſtaine us, if we obey his Goſpell. <hi>Let the good departure of my Soule to ſalvation, bee alwaies evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent to my faith,</hi> and I ſhall be the leſſe curious to care how darke and deadly it entred into my body. It is the going out more then the comming that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernes every hearer of Gods Goſpel. This was S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtines</hi> meditation, and ſhall be mine for ever; that my end may conclude my ſorrowes, and begin my joyes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The true cauſe.</head>
               <p>For the cauſe of this end we are taught by our Text to be ſinne, and in ſpeciall
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:1458:82"/>the ſinne of the Goſpell. Ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>religious honeſt men, and civill inſidels know not this ſinne, they have no light and leading unto it: Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience applies no ſuch fact to the Law, as to diſobey the Goſpell, neither does the Law trouble any man with accuſation of this ſin. It is ſolely and ſolitarily the Goſpels office to convince of this fault. To want faith in God is reproved by the Law; but in a Mediator, by the Goſpell: To want per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonall righteouſneſſe, is the crime the Law will charge us with; but to want the righteouſneſſe of another, muſt come to bee evinced by the Goſpell. Holineſſe of nature is what the Law
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:1458:83"/>requireth, and condemneth the contrary; but holineſſe of Grace infuſed by the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, is the light of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, and to bee deſtitute thereof is the greateſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation, <hi>Iohn</hi> 3.19.</p>
               <p>This muſt teach us firſt to diſtinguiſh the ſinnes of the Law and the Goſpell, &amp; how to aggravate them. Secondly, ſeeing faith and the Goſpell are free gifts, wee muſt neither bee cloſſe freinds unto nature, nor o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen friends unto grace. We have no power to reach ſo high as the Goſpell, or call for faith at our pleaſure: wee are more ready to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject both, and reaſon againſt them with the ſtubborne <hi>Iewes,</hi> than convinced and
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:1458:83"/>yeeld them our obedience. Thirdly, wee muſt looke to our danger. Turkes and Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars that never heard of the Goſpell, ſhall eſcape better than Chriſtians: They ſhall be beaten with few ſtripes for that little they have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, we with many for our great and graceleſſe neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lects: In ſtead of rods God will laſh us with Scorpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, who have neither an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered the utmoſt of our power, or greatneſſe of our meanes, <hi>Math.</hi> 11.15. and 13.12.</p>
               <p>Civil &amp; moral men under the Goſpell are in greateſt danger, becauſe they op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe their owne righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to Chriſts righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and will not be moved
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:1458:84"/>to maſter themſelves, in a meane conceite of their beſt proficiencies: Theſe are in danger to want faith, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is needleſſe for thoſe that have thoughts of fulneſſe in themſelves. Their vertues and good actions are all they boaſt of, and therefore theſe men prove barren under the Goſpell. With theſe full Phariſees wee have another ſort of people in as great danger upon a contrary ground; faith is their glory, and they ſeare not to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ee found with the beſt in Gods favour: Aske th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> in good earneſt, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> they were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced of ſinne, and they will bee briefe with you, that they ſcorne but to bee
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:1458:84"/>leſſe holy than the beſt, and to reprove them is audaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſlander: Why, but are you not ſinners? yes, for fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhion ſake they will not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny that, Are we not all ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners?</p>
               <p>But what ſay you to want of faith in Chriſt; to this they have a vulgar and groſſe anſwer; marry, God forbid I ſhould be ſo bad as not to beleeve in Chriſt; I thanke God I love him with my very heart, and ſo have done ever ſince I was borne. But were you never ſound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly convinced by the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell and Gods Spirit, of this great want? What? would you make us infidels? wee abhorre to thinke of ſuch queſtions: goe and aske
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:1458:85"/>them the Turkes, for we by the grace of God will never turne Turkes, and take part againſt Chriſt. But when came this perſwaſion into your hearts, and by what meanes was it wrought? I finde, <hi>Iohn</hi> 16.8, 9. a Spirit of conviction; what ſay you? Have you heard of this Spirit ſince you were baptized? how and in what manner hath this Spirit wrought in you? Truly we beleeve there is ſuch a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon in the Trinity, for ſo we were baptized; but for ſuch a gift, it is all one to us, as if there were no Spirit at all. Now (poore ſoules) you have put them beſides all their divinity, and convin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced them of that for which
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:1458:85"/>they give God thankes, bleſſing God they never wanted faith, which aſſures them they never had it; for to want it, is the way to have it, and to beleeve the contrary, an undoubted te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony of their dangerous preſumption. God open their eyes, and bring them to a better triall by the truth of his word.</p>
               <p>I will therefore deſcend into a more ſtrickt exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of the ſinne and the judgement in my text, and deale right downe in the whole worke of the convi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, <hi>Iohn</hi> 16.8. and then a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine repeate the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and ſummon up as many particulars as my me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory and Gods mercy ſhall
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:1458:86"/>ſuggeſt unto mee. I will reade this text alleadged, and deale by faire and capi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall titles, for the more firme and faithfull remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of my Reader, in all that followeth.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A glorious Kingdome.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iohn</hi> 16.8, <hi>And when he is come, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There bee two great Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors come from the Father into the world, by whom he will convince the world before he judge it, and theſe two ſucceed the one the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; the firſt abſents him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, and the other comes in his roome. To finde Chriſt a ſucceſſor in man, is the crime of the Church of
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:1458:86"/>
                  <hi>Rome,</hi> of which they are now aſhamed, and by cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection mend their Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors and bid them ſay, the Pope is the Vicar of Chriſt, and Succeſſor of S. <hi>Peter.</hi> But by their leave, they yet want an <hi>Index expurgatorius,</hi> to expunge and wipe out the Pope, and put in a more equall for Chriſt, left by himſelfe, when he left this earth, fitter to bee both Chriſts Vicar and Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſous. Theſe two excellent Teachers undertake the conviction of the world be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the condemnation of it. So dealt Ieſus Chriſt with the <hi>Iewes.</hi> We will en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>large our ſelves in the worke of the Trinity, and bee ample in the view of
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:1458:87"/>their Kingdome.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The excellent and admirable adminiſtration of Gods King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</head>
               <p>There bee three perſons in the Divine nature that worketh all things, yet are all things wrought in a wonderfull and moſt di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct and unconfuſed man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner. The Father of himſelfe and to himſelfe worketh all things, and ſo is the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and end of every acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.6. The progreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion from this beginning, and regreſsion to this end, is the rareſt and ſweeteſt myſteries in the Bible. In the progreſſion the Father goes on by the Sonne, and both Father and Sonne by
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:1458:87"/>the bleſſed Spirit; and here beginnes the immediate ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome within, the Spirit al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes taking the poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of it. I will open clearely this Divine and raviſhing ſecret, and ſet men on work with no new notion, but an old truth; for I abhorre to deflect from the wayes of Antiquity.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the progreſsion and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſsion of the Kingdome from and to the Father.</head>
               <p>S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Paul</hi> ſetling true religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on upon the ſureſt pillars, pluckes downe the rotten and ragged pillars of Pagans and Papiſts, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.6. <hi>To us there is but one God, the Father of whom are all things,
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:1458:88"/>and wee to him. &amp;c.</hi> Many gods confound themſelves in their beginning and end, and therefore if creatures were from them, they ſhould bee confounded in their originall, &amp; this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion would breed a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, they ſhould not know whom to ſerve: But wee (ſaith the Apoſtle) have this errour corrected in one God, neither neede wee be confounded with many perſons, for they are our beſt helpe in religion. Take the firſt perſon, make him the beginning of all crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and our end in ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, and we ſhall know both to whom wee are behol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, and to whom we owe our thankes. The Heathen
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:1458:88"/>have no ſuch knowledge, they neither know Author nor end of their actions &amp; praiſe.</p>
               <p>In this wee agree with them, that to goe to God without a mediator is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption in both, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they have their many lords to goe by to their ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny gods, and are here againe confounded in their praiers, not knowing to what Saint to turne. Fryer <hi>Teitis,</hi> made a ſermon that Saints might bee ſerved with the Lords prayer; for that it was a common queſtion with the <hi>Romane</hi> Chanters to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, to whom do you ſay your <hi>Pater noſter.</hi> This is a ſtraine of the old religion, and many lords of the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then,
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:1458:89"/>and therefore Chriſt being put out, or ſhuffled in with the multitude, it was no marvaile ſuch a queſtion ſhould bee raiſed; for to God muſt we goe by a me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diator: but <hi>Paul</hi> in the progreſſion of our religion hath given us better dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, that as the Father by one Lord Ieſus Chriſt hath made all things; ſo we, if we will proceede aright, muſt by the ſame Lord Ieſus Chriſt, and no other, goe to the ſame Father, and ſo in concluſion, after a long and glorious perigrination up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on earth, we ſhal be brought to the Father, that hee in us (as <hi>Paul</hi> witneſſeth, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.28.) may be all in all.</p>
               <pb n="103" facs="tcp:1458:89"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Of the Sonnes mediation in this Kingdome.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It was expedient for us that the Father ſhould ſend his Sonne; for wee which are the beſt of his creatures, being lapſed, cannot with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Chriſt ſerve our end. He is <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.6. <hi>Ephſ.</hi> 4.5. 1 <hi>Tim:</hi> 2.5. and 6<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>15. &amp;c. the alone mediator, and power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full potentate with God for us. For this end he is incar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, and to this purpoſe he lives and dies, riſeth from the dead, conferreth forty dayes of this Kingdome, <hi>Act.</hi> 1.3. and ſo departeth into heaven, and makes fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther way for progreſſe in this kingdome, and to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect this, ſends his Spirit,
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:1458:90"/>telling us of a truth how expedient this is for them that are now to bee left to preach his kingdome, to have him depart that the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Doctor may come. Expedient and neceſſary for all that are to be ſaved; for Chriſt being riſen againe, had all power and iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment from his Father, <hi>Mat.</hi> 28. &amp;c. The preſent executi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of this power, had beene a woefull thing with the world, being both unrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous and unholy. Chriſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed it, and therefore will not preſently deſtroy it, but commands in the ſame place, that proclamati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of his power bee made; and being with his He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raulds unto the end, will in
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:1458:90"/>the end call the world to an account, and ſhew both his power, &amp; their iudgement. This great Embaſſage into all the world had need of ſome noble Agent to leade the way, and bee preſent with the holy Apoſtles and their ſucceſſours: and this honourable perſon is the third perſon in the bleſſed Trinity, in whoſe hands and adminiſtration Gods King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome is for this preſent age, and of which wee are now to ſpeake.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Kingdome of Grace.</head>
               <p>In the Lords prayer wee petition, <hi>Thy kingdome come,</hi> our underſtandings at this day abbreviate this petition, and are defective in the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion of it, and ſo conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:1458:91"/>our prayers come ſhort of their dutie, &amp; deale with God for no more than they know. We wil (God aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting) inlarge our thoughts in the regreſſion of the Kingdome, from the Spirit to the Father againe, and ſhew, Firſt, the adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Spirit. Secondly, of the Sonne. Thirdly, of the Father; and ſo teach you plainely to pray for the Kingdome of grace, King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of power, and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of glory when all is returned to the Father.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Kingdome within and ſeated in mens hearts.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 17.20, 21. The Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſees would have a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome by obſervation: but
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:1458:91"/>Chriſt knowing the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes adminiſtration, firſt to reſt in the Spirit and grace thereof, takes away that error, and according to the nature of the Kingdome ſets and ſeates it within; for ſuch as is the government; ſuch muſt bee the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. The government ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall, therefore the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome ſpirituall. Grace and the Spirit of grace, carry no outward pompe and exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall ſtate; but are all glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous within: And this is that kingdome that ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth violence without, and is oppreſſed by rebels and traitours to the Lord Ieſus, and their owne ſoules.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Kingdome of violence.</head>
               <p>The Kingdome of Gods
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:1458:92"/>Spirit is the moſt pious and peaceable Kingdome in the world; yet ſuffereth more than all kingdomes, as ſhall now appeare, <hi>Math.</hi> 11.12. <hi>Luke</hi> 16.16. Gods king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome under the Law and the Prophets ſuffered vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, and ſo ſhall it under <hi>Iohn,</hi> Chriſt, his holy Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, and Miniſters, doe for the time of the Goſpell. I know theſe texts are ſtrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to another ſenſe, and ſo my ſelfe have beene a fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lower of this violence, till that man of God M. <hi>Ioſeph Meade,</hi> cleared my ſight by his induſtrious and judici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous obſervation of the text. It may bee we are both de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, &amp; it becomes hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble men not to bee peremp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:1458:92"/>in croſſing and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trolling others. We all agree of the violence offered to the Kingdome of grace, and diſagree in the proofe of it by theſe texts. Heare then mine arguments and reaſons which I ſubject to the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of the Prophets.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Chriſts anſwer by the Law &amp; the Prophets, ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the conformity be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the old and the new Teſtament; the ancient and ſurrogate <hi>Iſrael</hi> of God. Violence waited upon the Church before Chriſt, and ſo will it now, and after him. It is your error (O fooliſh <hi>Iewes</hi>) to looke now for a kingdome by obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and to ſee your ſelves more redeemed from the
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:1458:93"/>
                  <hi>Romines</hi> and men, than from devils, &amp; your ſleves, more deadly enemies: You have more neede to have Sathan diſplaced, than your ſelves placed in a temporall Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy: I am come to ſave your ſoules from ſinnes and not your bodies from bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage. Secondly, <hi>Iohn</hi> that now preacheth the new Kingdome is in priſon, <hi>Math.</hi> 11.2. and muſt loſe his head: I looke for no greater favour, my Apoſtles will ſucceede mee, and by ſucceſſion it will laſt till I come and take the Eagles off the carkeiſe, <hi>Luk.</hi> 17.37, 3. The Kingdome is prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, a thing that the world hateth, and therefore will every man have a blow at
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:1458:93"/>it, and violent men will prey upon it: this reading the texts will render, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all renting and tearing the phraſes. 4. The word ſignifying violence, or vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent men, was never taken by any Author for inward violence, or motions free and voluntary, but for out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward force and externall power, putting others to be patients of their perſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and puniſhments.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Spirits conqueſt.</head>
               <p>God is not wanting to his poore ſervants, but gives courage and conſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in all their oppreſſions. The Spirit ſets up ſuch a Kingdome in the heart and ſoules of Gods people, that no paine or perill can pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaile
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:1458:94"/>to conquer their faith and confidence. They are reſolved to carry their lives in their hands, &amp; rather dye than deny that truth that the holy Ghoſt hath taught them. This ſpiritual I King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome ſubdues all King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, yea, more than all Kingdomes, for it gaines that victory over our ſelves which is more than any earthly conqueſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Conqueſt by convict on.</head>
               <p>The greateſt oppoſition to the Spirit of grace, is in our ſelves. It were eaſie to ruine all the world, and in ſuch conqueſts and conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions men have ſhewed their might and manhood: but to enter the houſe held by the ſtrong man, both of
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:1458:94"/>corruption in our ſelves, and ſuggeſtion of Sathan out of our ſelves, is a potent and powerfull worke of grace; Gods Spirit alone is able to beate downe theſe holds, helpe in the conqueſt of our ſelves, and ſubjection to the Kingdome preached and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered vs in the Goſpell. He it is that brings in faith to beleeve, and excludes infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delity; That raiſeth up in us the comfort of Chriſts righteouſneſſe, and rejecteth our owne; That teacheth us holyneſſe, and how to deny all ungodlineſſe, and every worldly luſt, and to live ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berly in our ſelves, righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly to others, and godly to our King and Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der: of the ſeverall bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:1458:95"/>of conviction, we ſhall intreate afterwards, and ſhew what ſinnes are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>victed and controuled in us, and how wee ought to ſee them, and ſorrow for them, &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Conviction by ſupportation.</head>
               <p>The Spirit in this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of grace, worketh &amp; effecteth another ſtrange worke and operation upon the world, in giving his ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects power of conqueſt in trials, and to triumph over the world, and all its wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kings and miſchiefes, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.37. <hi>In all theſe things we are more than conquerours:</hi> What things? even the worſt that the world can doe unto us, and that is to make us Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyres, and themſelves mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therers,
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:1458:95"/>yea even to mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther themſelves to ſee us ſo little affected with their torments. We ſtand ſtill and do nothing, and ſee our ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of God. To conquer by paſſion is cleane contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to the world; for ſo the world is conquered, and hee that ſuffers becomes ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to another: but we are ſlaine (ſaith the Apoſtle) and our ſlaughter is our vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory; nay, more than victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry; in ſo doing we conquer the conquerours, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand our oppreſſors. More than conquerours, is more than any <hi>Caeſar</hi> achieved un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, or ever Monarch effected in his greateſt victories. Who can ſay ſo, but Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians? Emperours have
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:1458:96"/>conquered with difficultie, and loſt with greater facili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty all their kingdomes. They have beene leſſe than conquerours, and never got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten victory, but left it to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers to gaine it from them. O the honour of this ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall kingdome, and excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency of grace, that even thriveth beſt vnder oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions and worldly vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The regreſsion of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</head>
               <p>All the honour of this Kingdome redoundeth un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Chriſt, and ſhall then ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare when he appeares to take his Kingdome &amp; great dominion. He ſhould have had no ſubjects but for the Spirit, and none ſo victori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous,
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:1458:96"/>but for Martyres, who as they have firſt honoured Chriſt by death, ſhall of him againe bee firſt graced with life. Thoſe that are alive and converted, ſhall bee a glory to Chriſt, as hee will bee a glory to them. It is for the perſons in the ſacred Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, mutually to raiſe glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one to another: Wee are therefore <hi>ordine retrogrado,</hi> come from the kingdome of grace to the Kingdome of power, from the admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of the Spirit, to the adminiſtration of the Son, and ſeeke after three things as glorious as the former, and yet more outward, but not leſſe ſpirituall; for per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection in the Trinity, is both wayes obſerued and
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:1458:97"/>effected in progreſſion, the Father perfects his worke in the Sonne, and the Sonne in the Spirit: ſo in regreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the holy Ghoſt perfects grace in power, and the Son perfects power in glory. We will ſpeake of the Sons taking, ruling, and delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring up of this kingdome of power.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Chriſts taking of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of power.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.5. mention is made of <hi>a world to come,</hi> and the ſubjectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thereof to Chriſt. This wee ſee not (ſaith the Apoſtle) as yet accompli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, but wee ſee Ieſus Chriſt crowned and made a King in heaven. His pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence on earth as yet wee have not, ſave in the holy
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:1458:97"/>Ghoſt. But hee will appeare in his body, and take this Kingdome and whole world to himſelfe, and turne out of it all the ungodly in the earth. His enemies that would not ſuffer him to reigne over them by his Goſpell, are then to bee brought before him and ſlaine in his preſence.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The taking of his great power.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Revel.</hi> 11.17. At the laſt trumpet, and the laſt woe, all Kingdomes fall to Chriſt. But how I pray you? marke the text, <hi>He ſhall take to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe his great power, and reigne.</hi> To himſelfe imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately, to himſelfe for forme and manner of go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment. He left it in the hands of the Spirit, and now
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:1458:98"/>takes it againe to himſelfe, no more depriving the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of the honour of it in the re-aſſumption, than hee did himſelfe, when he depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed it into the hands of his Spirit. Now the queſtion will bee how this is done? The anſwer is, with great power; greater than ever before; for it deſtroyes them all, that now deſtroy the earth.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>How is it taken?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Daniel</hi> aſſoi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es this doubt, and makes it glorious and wonderfull in his extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary deſcription of it, <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.9, 10. &amp;c. Firſt, the Lord Ieſus takes it from his enemies, and caſts downe their thrones, and makes them ſeates for his Saints.
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:1458:98"/>
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.7. he takes it from the laſt beaſt, even becauſe of the little horne, and his blaſphemous and bloody words. Secondly, hee takes it from the Ancient of daies, who in a glorious and moſt illuſtrious manner inſtalles the Lord Ieſus into his king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. Thirdly, he is atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded and waited upon by the innumerable company of Angels, by whom hee is brought to the Ancient of dayes. Reade the reſt and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mite at this inauguration and ſolemnization of the day of Chriſts coronation upon earth, who now in heaven is crowned with glory and immortality.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>When it is taken.</head>
               <p>2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.1. At the <hi>Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phanie</hi>
                  <pb n="122" facs="tcp:1458:99"/>of his kingdome, <hi>Marke</hi> 13.26. <hi>Luke</hi> 21.27. when the powers of heaven are ſhaken, and the ſtarres that ſhine in them are hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled to the ground. Earthly potentates that are advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced above others ſhall bee made low. The fall of ſuch ſtarres will not hinder the ſight of Chriſt, but honour it. Other ſtarres being bigger than the earth, would over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lay it and men, and ſuffer no man to ſtand upon earth to ſee the Lord Ieſus come in the clouds of heaven with power and great glory.</p>
               <p>Hee muſt bee ſeene of all eyes, and therefore it is moſt ſafe to give the ſenſe of the Scriptures by the Scriptures, and to ſay of this day as of
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:1458:99"/>the former ſhadowes of it in <hi>Babylon</hi> and <hi>Aegypt, Iſa.</hi> 13.10. and 14.12, 13. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 32.7, 8. <hi>The starres of heaven and the conſtellations thereof ſhall not give their light. The Sunne ſhall bee darkned in his going forth, and the Moone ſhall not cauſe her light to ſhine, the bright lights of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven are put out,</hi> when <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raoh</hi> falleth by the <hi>Babiloni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> and <hi>Lucifer</hi> ſonne of the morning, aſcended into hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, above the heights of the clouds, and ſtarres them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to bee like the moſt High, comes downe to the ground; when by the <hi>Medes</hi> and <hi>Perſians Belſhazzar</hi> is pulled from the orbe of his height and honour. Chriſt the bright ſhining ſtarre of
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:1458:100"/>
                  <hi>Iacob,</hi> and the advanced Scep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of <hi>Iſrae,</hi> is riſen, and ſhall riſe to ſmite all corners, and ſubdue all Nations. Let us therefore advance him from the taking of the kingdome, to the ruling of it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Chriſts ruling and reig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning in his kingdome.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.14. On this day <hi>dominion</hi> is given to Chriſt, <hi>Zech.</hi> 14.9. <hi>One Lord, one name,</hi> and that over all the earth. In this day will hee reigne in and over all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinde. <hi>Rev.</hi> 11, 15. Now the world does not acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge him for one Lord, as being ruled by many; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther does it worſhip him by one name, as being diſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted into many religions: but this will Chriſt remove at
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:1458:100"/>his day, and rule by a more equall power, and uniforme worſhip. <hi>Paul</hi> is our wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.24, 25, 26. &amp;c. that the end and delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry up of this kingdome to God, even the Father, cannot be, till rule, authority, and power of devils in hell, men upon earth, and even death, the laſt of enemies be fully vanquiſhed and ſubdu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: and for this purpoſe, I might produce all the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets and holy Apoſtles, ſpeaking glorious things of Chriſts reigning and ruling at the ſound of the laſt trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet, and comming of the laſt woe, <hi>Rev.</hi> 10.7. All the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets are witneſſes; and S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Peter</hi> ſpeaking of the ſame thing, adds to them all the
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:1458:101"/>Apoſtles, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3 2.</p>
               <p>They have ill done, that have muzled up the mouthes of the Prophets with a Conſummation and concluſion in Chriſts incarnation. The <hi>Iewes</hi> diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute, <hi>Dan.</hi> 2.35. and 7.11. That Meſſiah muſt come when the Monarchies are as chaffe before the winde, and quite blowne out of the world: When the feete and foundation, even the ten di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided toes in the bottome of that terrible image are cruſhed, and conquered by the victorious ſtone, whoſe kingdome becomes a moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, filling the whole earth. Hee muſt then take place when the laſt beaſt is ſlaine, his little horne (ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:1458:101"/>eyes to watch the ten hornes, and to ſpeake blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemies againſt God) is conſumed. Vtter ruine muſt befall all Chriſts enemies before he take from the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient of dayes his dominion and univerſall command o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver all the world. Hence they would conclude againſt Chriſtians, that their Meſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ah is not come, for they urge us by our owne confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, that hee came in the dayes of <hi>Auguſtus Caeſar,</hi> when the laſt beaſt flouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed moſt, &amp; was farre enough from chaffe or clay: it was not then come to the tenne toes, or ten hornes, in which it hath held to this day, and therefore as yet Meſſiah is not yet come.</p>
               <pb n="128" facs="tcp:1458:102"/>
               <p>Stay (ſtubborne <hi>Iewes</hi>) wee will not take theſe texts from you but grant them, and yet deny your conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent: for Meſſiah by the teſtimony of the ſame Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet muſt firſt come to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deeme, <hi>Dan.</hi> 9.24. Your weekes are gone, and might aſſure you Meſſiah is come, and hath made reconciliati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for you &amp; us. He is gone to heaven, and hath left his kingdome in the hands of his Spirit; againſt him you have rebelled, and brought upon your ſelves the end in my text: repent and hee will returne to you, and you ſhal ſee him, as <hi>Daniel</hi> hath deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered unto you, and witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by an Apoſtle of Chriſt, <hi>Act.</hi> 3.19, 20, 21. and is the
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:1458:102"/>onely and laſt reaſon of the ſtay and ſlackeneſſe of his comming, and performance of his promiſe to you in ſpecial, 2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.9. Would God you were at as good agreement with our holy Apoſtles, as wee are with your Prophets, we ſhould ſoone and ſuddenly both meete in this kingdome of power.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>Balaams prophecie, Numb.</hi> 24.15. <hi>to the end.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Of this kingdome <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laam</hi> is forced to ſpeake, and by a ſtarre and his ſhadowes gives in parables an excellent proſpective for the view of things a farre off but not nigh, at a great diſtance of time, but not preſent in this age. The ſtar
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:1458:103"/>ſmites <hi>Moab</hi> in the ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes of it: but it ſhall <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wall all the ſonnes of Seth,</hi> im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately by it ſelfe and laſt appearance, <hi>Amalecke</hi> the firſt of Nations is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed by the prayers of <hi>Moſes,</hi> and ſword of <hi>Ioſhua,</hi> true types of Chriſt; and <hi>Chittim</hi> the laſt of Nations ſhall by Chriſt himſelfe im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately periſh. Of both theſe it is ſaid more than of all the reſt, <hi>They ſhall periſh for ever.</hi> The reaſon is plaine, <hi>Amaleke</hi> was the firſt that fought with the <hi>ancient Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael</hi> in the wilderneſſe to hinder their paſſage into <hi>Canaan;</hi> and therefore muſt be ſmitten for ever. Now is the <hi>ſurrogate Iſrael</hi> of God in the like wilderneſſe,
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:1458:103"/>
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 12.6, 14. and <hi>Chittim</hi> onely makes warre with it, and therefore as <hi>Amalek</hi> of old, muſt periſh for ever.</p>
               <p>To <hi>Aſhur</hi> all Nations were ſmitten by the ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes of the riſing ſtarre: but from <hi>Aſhur</hi> to <hi>Chittim,</hi> the ſtarre Chriſt, by conjun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction and ſecret influence, makes one Starre ſmite ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and as he ſets the. <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyptians againſt the Aegypti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, Iſa.</hi> 19.2. ſo be ſets <hi>Aſhur</hi> againſt <hi>Aſhur,</hi> &amp; <hi>Chittim</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Chittim,</hi> &amp; both againſt <hi>Heber,</hi> till his honour come by Chriſt. <hi>Aſhur</hi> is the land of <hi>Aſſyria, Chittim</hi> is put for the <hi>Iles of the Gentiles. Aſhur</hi> begins with <hi>Nimrod, Gen.</hi> 10. a ſonne of curſed <hi>Cham.</hi> He is the firſt mighty hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:1458:104"/>after honour, and begins his kingdome with <hi>Babylon,</hi> the building of confuſion, both for religion, language, and love. From <hi>Babylon</hi> hee hunts into <hi>Aſhur</hi> or the land of <hi>Aſſiria,</hi> and builds <hi>Nineveh,</hi> and at length fils the great Continent of the world with his Monarchy. The <hi>Babylonians</hi> take it and hold it, till the <hi>Medes</hi> and <hi>Perſians</hi> become Lords of their kingdome and Conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent. Thus the Lord daſheth kingdome againſt king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and like a potters veſſell breaketh them one upon another.</p>
               <p>From the <hi>Continent</hi> to the <hi>Iles of the Gentiles,</hi> the ſame Chriſt tranſlateth the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchies, and ends them in
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:1458:104"/>the Sonnes of <hi>laphet. Chit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tim</hi> a ſonne of <hi>Iaphet, Gen.</hi> 10. being divided from the Continent by the Seas, finds poſterity in time to paſſe the Seas, and by ſhips from his Coaſts carrieth <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander</hi> the Great, <hi>Dan.</hi> 2.32, and 7.6. and 11.3. 1 <hi>Maccab.</hi> 1.1, with his Army; who killeth <hi>Darius,</hi> and from <hi>Aſhur</hi> to <hi>Chittim</hi> tranſlateth his kingdome. The riſing ſtarre knowes how by his ſecret opperation to ſtirre up <hi>Chittim</hi> againſt <hi>Chittim,</hi> and to puniſh the Iles for Idolatry and tyranny; he ſets the inhabitants thereof to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether by the eares for their ſinnes, and by the <hi>Romanes</hi> at length brings the Monarchy from the <hi>Graecians</hi> to us, and
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:1458:105"/>ſettles the glory of it in <hi>Rome,</hi> where it ſlouriſhed to the birth of Chriſt, and long after. At length this maſſie monarchie drencht in blood, even the beſt blood, the blood of Saints, began to reele and totter, and from one Caeſar fals to ten Kings, from yron legs ſtrongly united to ten toes weakely divided; they hang upon the ſame feet of the Image, but their diviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is fatall to the Empire.</p>
               <p>Theſe toes in the Image, and ten hornes on the head of the laſt beaſt, are the laſt of <hi>Chittim,</hi> and remaine to this day for perdition by Chriſt, as farre as <hi>Iaphet</hi> is not perſwaded to dwell in the tents of <hi>Shem, Gen.</hi> 9.22.
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:1458:105"/>what now remaines but that the third Sonne of <hi>Noah</hi> alwayes choſen of God for his chiefe ſervant, ſhould obtaine the kingdome, and that <hi>Heber</hi> hitherto affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted by <hi>Aſhur</hi> and <hi>Chittim,</hi> ſhould be made glorious at the comming of the Lord Ieſus? The promiſe of the new heavens and the new earth is made to them, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 65.17, 18. and 66.22. this quoted by S. <hi>Peter,</hi> 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.13. applyed by him to the <hi>Iewes,</hi> and by them to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected in the day of judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, when hee takes his great power to reigne. The ſame is repeated, <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.1. and applyed to <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> verſ. 2. of this as a myſtery, S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeakes, <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.25.
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:1458:106"/>and quotes <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> who <hi>Iſa.</hi> 59 18. brings it in with the ſubverſion of <hi>Chittim,</hi> or the Ilands. What ſhall I ſay more? let <hi>Peter</hi> expound <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> and <hi>Iſaiah, Peter;</hi> and we, ſhall quickly reſolve of this myſtery.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the length of the day of Iudgement.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Zech.</hi> 14.7. Having ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of <hi>Ieruſalems</hi> deſolation as Chriſt did, <hi>Math.</hi> 24. comes in the like manner to their conſolation, and ſaies, <hi>The Lord my God ſhall come, and all the Saints with thee;</hi> then deſcribes the day of judgement; 1. <hi>by light,</hi> to manifeſt all deeds of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. 2. by the <hi>purity</hi> of this light, <hi>it ſhall not be cleare and darke,</hi> that is, one part light
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:1458:106"/>and another darke, like a day of creation, but it ſhall be light without darkneſſe. 3. the <hi>unity</hi> of this day, it is to be one how long ſoever; Chriſt will not be interrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in his kingdome, or ſtayed in his judgement. 4. the <hi>knowledge</hi> of this day, both when it ſhall begin, how long it ſhould conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue, and when it ſhal end, is onely belonging to the King that ſhall rule in it. 5. to take away all doubt of a day, it ſhall not conſiſt of the parts of a naturall and created day, <hi>not night and day,</hi> which by the ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of heaven are perpetual: but this ſhall be a voluntary and arbitrary day, depending upon the will and motion of
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:1458:107"/>Chriſt, and no meaſure of ſtarres. 6. contrary to all the dayes of the creation, this ſhall bee <hi>light at the evening,</hi> yea, then ſhall bee the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt light in the regreſſion of the kingdome trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phantly from Chriſt to his and our Father.</p>
               <p>The light of grace breaks forth into the light of po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer, and the light of power into the light of glory. What then ſhall be the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of this day, called the great, notable, and terrible day of the Lord? <hi>Ioel</hi> 2.32. <hi>Iude</hi> verſ. 6. <hi>Rev</hi> 16.14. &amp;c. ſhall it vaniſh in the twinckling of an eye, and that myſtery, <hi>Rev.</hi> 10.7. paſſe in a moment? No aſſuredly, wee are reſolved by Chriſt,
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:1458:107"/>that it ſhal be a day compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hending dayes, <hi>Luke</hi> 17.22, 26. many dayes that ſhall af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foord times of refreſhing and reſtitution, <hi>Act.</hi> 3.19. dayes and times ſhall be up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this great day, and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is faire to favour this ſenſe. Chriſt, takes his king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and power upon this day to reigne and rule, and therefore it is reaſonable to yeeld him ſome time before the delivery of it up to his Father, to ſhew the glory and the excellency of it. It agrees well with the regreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to perfection, that ſome ſtay ſhould bee made, for the honour of <hi>Heber,</hi> and glory of the King.</p>
               <p>Shall I offer other texts, and tell you what they teach
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:1458:108"/>you to beleeve? I will not command your faith, where it is fit for me to ſuſpend my owne. It were preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to reſolve before the iſſue, and reade the ridle be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it be plaine in the acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and event, as well as in the prophecy and predicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. <hi>Zech.</hi> 14.8. the Prophet ſeemes to deſcribe unto us the day of judgement, and to compute it by a day in <hi>ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer</hi> and in <hi>winter,</hi> and then the great day will mount to a yeere at the leaſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 65.20. If <hi>the new hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens and the new earth,</hi> fall out upon this great day, as <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> ſeemes to expound it, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.13. then <hi>Iſaiah</hi> will ſeeme to ſpeake of an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred yeeres at the leaſt,
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:1458:108"/>2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.8. <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.4. If one day in <hi>Peter</hi> bee a day of judgement, as the verſe up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which it is inferred ſeemes to ſpeake plainely; then ſuch a great <hi>day with the Lord</hi> Chriſt, or to the Lord Chriſt (as <hi>Zechary</hi> phraſeth it) <hi>is as a thouſand yeares, and a thouſand yeares, as ſuch a day: One day,</hi> ſaies <hi>Zechary; one day,</hi> ſaies <hi>Peter,</hi> and both ſeeme to ſay one thing.</p>
               <p>But a thouſand yeeres will be put for eternity, and ſo no time is expreſſed, but that which waits upon God, and ſheweth him to be eternall: but yet S. <hi>Iohn</hi> will anſwer this, and by an invincible ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument take it from us, if his thouſand yeeres have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:1458:109"/>with <hi>Peter</hi> to the ſame day; for after eternity there is no hiſtory of time, or rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of any ſucceſſion; but S. <hi>Iohn</hi> placeth <hi>a little ſeaſon</hi> after the thouſand yeeres, and that wipes out the opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of a thouſand yeeres to be put for ever. I will nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther diſpute nor relate any more, wee have too many new opinions, this is old enough, and by carnall Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaſts made both odious and erronious. It is fitteſt wee bee ſilent, and prepare for this great day, let it bee of what ſength the author plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth; for to his liking muſt it laſt, not in living to carnall luſts, but heavenly joyes. God give us grace to looke for it, and inlarge our petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:1458:109"/>with calling for the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of grace, in the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of power. Wee live (God knowes) as if we were ſome ſeven months birth, vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall, but weake. The king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of power will rouze us up; for Chriſt takes it not onely to deſtroy our e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies, but to ſtirre up our graces. <hi>In the new heavens and new earth righteouſneſſe ſhall dwell;</hi> it is now baniſhed from kingdomes, <hi>Chittim</hi> oppreſſeth it, and a few ſons of <hi>Iaphet</hi> are perſwaded to imbrace it: but the time ſhal come, when it ſhall poſſeſſe mankinde plentifully, and not <hi>Shem,</hi> but all the ſonnes of <hi>Seth</hi> ſhall imbrace it. <hi>Numb.</hi> 24.17. <hi>Moab</hi> as an enemy periſheth: <hi>Sheth</hi> as a
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:1458:110"/>friend is ſubdued, that Chriſt may have ſubjects. I will touch the great change that Chriſts kingdome ſhall make in the world at his comming, and ſo haſten the returne of it to the Father.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Alterations by Chriſts comming.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 32.15, 16, 17. &amp;c. The Spirit that now is come to the Gentiles, and departed from the Iewes, muſt againe be powred on them, &amp; then is wrought in the world: wonderfull change. 1. The <hi>field</hi> of <hi>Chittim</hi> that now flouriſheth in the hands of wicked men, ſhall bee turned into a <hi>forreſt,</hi> and made as barren and deſolate as the wilderneſſe. 2. The <hi>forreſt</hi> of the Iewes ſhall alter into a
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:1458:110"/>
                  <hi>fertile field,</hi> and by Chriſt himſelfe ſhall be made gio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious. Thirdly, this goodly and flouriſhing field ſhall be planted and ſowne with <hi>judgement</hi> and <hi>righteouſneſſe,</hi> they ſhall even dwell in it; and take up the whole poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion of it. Fourthly, the fruit ſhall be <hi>peace</hi> and <hi>quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,</hi> no warre, no moleſtati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſhall diſturbe them. Fift<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, this Harveſt of happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe ſhall be with aſſurance for ever. When Chriſt takes his power to reigne, none ſhall any more rule over him or his. Both hee and his Saints have ſuffered of this wicked world, but the woe thereof <hi>commeth quickely,</hi> and ſpeedy ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance will pay for all de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>layes.
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:1458:111"/>Be admoniſhed (my brethren) you are by the conſent of Divines, come to the <hi>ſecond woe, Rev.</hi> 9.13. above 300 yeeres agoe. The next is the day of judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and is ever delivered with this <hi>Item, Behold it commeth quickely, Rev.</hi> 11.14. adde to this, <hi>Luke</hi> 18 8. <hi>Revel.</hi> 3.7. and 16.15. and 21.12. Other woes lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger and laſt long, as being executed by men: but this will be ſpeedy, as being im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately done by Chriſt himſelfe, who will not ſtand long about his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, though his friends may enjoy a longer time of rejoycing in his preſence.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="147" facs="tcp:1458:111"/>
               <head>The delivery up of his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome to his Father.</head>
               <p>1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.24. compared with 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.1. teach us the <hi>Epiphany</hi> and <hi>end</hi> of Chriſts adminiſtration, and wee have heard what falls out betweene theſe two termes. I muſt needs con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive it abſurd, till better reaſon convince me to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive of an Epiphany of a kingdome and an end toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: let who will ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive and conjecture, I am not as yet of their minde; ſome duration and ſucceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of time will be from the Epiphany to the end, when the end is come (beſt knowne to Chriſt) hee will returne all to the Father:
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:1458:112"/>but you will object, <hi>Revel.</hi> 11.15. <hi>Hee ſhall reigne for ever and ever.</hi> I anſwer, the delivery up of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, is not an excluſion of Chriſt from reigning, for as the Father reigneth in the Sonne, and both of them in holy Ghoſt: ſo in the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion, the holy Ghoſt reigneth in the Sonne, and both of them in the I ather. O raviſhing Societie, and bleſſed Communion wee ſhall enjoy in our Fathers houſe, when all is given up unto him, and yet in him all to be enjoyed. In him we enjoy Chriſt, and the bleſſed Spirit; we are no loſers but gainers by theſe wayes of Divine and deepe wiſedome.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="149" facs="tcp:1458:112"/>
               <head>The regreſſion of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome to the Father.</head>
               <p>1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.28. <hi>That God may be all in all, v.</hi> 24. <hi>God even the Father.</hi> God eſſentially ſhall bleſſe us, but the Father in ſpeciall ſhall be glorified in us. This was Chriſts pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er upon earth, <hi>Iohn</hi> 17.21. That we might be one in the bleſſed Trinitie, as they are one in themſelves, and have all conſpired to make us happy. Chriſt prayeth they may be perfect in one, that they may be where he is now, &amp;c. The holy Ghoſt and the Sonne conclude in the Father, and ſo muſt wee for our full happineſſe, <hi>Zech.</hi> 14.16. Why not the Paſſeover to be kept in the
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:1458:113"/>great day ſpoken of before? this was the greateſt feaſt in <hi>Iſrael:</hi> but the <hi>feaſt of Tabernacles</hi> hath a more apt alluſion to thoſe times. Our Manſions are in heaven; as long as we ſtay upon earth, though under aſſured ſafety and freedome from danger, yet we are not at the beſt. In the Kingdome of Grace we are well and happy. In the Kingdome of power we are better and more happy: but in the Kingdome of Glory we are beſt of all.</p>
               <p>We have thus farre di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſed, and I hope tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſed no rule in Religion. Wee can eaſily recall our ſelves to our firſt intention, concerning the comming of the holy Ghoſt. <hi>And
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:1458:113"/>when he is come, he ſhall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince the world of ſinne, and of righteouſneſſe, and of judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of Sinne.</head>
               <p>That is, want of faith in Chriſt, the ſigne of all ſinne, for we can expect no diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge without it. All ſinne in one ſinne is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced of the Law, we are guilty in <hi>Adam,</hi> and of this ſinne wee are guilty in the Goſpel. The ſinnes of the Law are ſtrong enough to condemne us, but this firme brings in our great condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 3.19. the Law is not that light that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines life in it, that light is Chriſt, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 1.14. He came into the world both as the
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:1458:114"/>light and life of it, and yet men loved darkeneſſe more than light, not onely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe their deeds were morrally evill, but becauſe they eſteemed not to have them mended by this new principle of faith in Chriſt. Infidels come not to the light of the Goſpel, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that does moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince them of ſinne. The Law is more ſparing than the Goſpel, for it chargeth man no further than of originall and actuall ſinne. But the Goſpel extends to his wants of ſuch faith, righteouſneſſe and holineſſe as the Law leaves at liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. It commands us faith in God, and is ſilent of faith in Chriſt. It bids us bee
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:1458:114"/>righteous, but not in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. It bids us be holy, but that is from our owne ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues, and not ſpirituall gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces.</p>
               <p>The Spirits light is too ſtrong for weake eyes to looke upon it. It blunts and blindes him to thinke his deeds ſo ill, as God does not approve the beſt of them. It is ſtrange to him to beleeve, that without faith in Chriſt, nothing that is done by him is accepted of God. He conceives bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of himſelfe, and truſts that his good meanings, and vertuous actions are not ſo out of requeſt with GOD, but he ſhall gaine ſome favour and friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip at Gods hands, to be
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:1458:115"/>eſteemed of better then of the worſt and moſt wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked man. Hee muſt there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore know that if the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel prove him guiltie of the want of faith, no ſinne is ſpared or pardoned any more to him than the lew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt liver in the world. Hee muſt therefore learne to love the truth of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, and come to the light thereof, that his deeds may be made manifeſt, that they are wrought in God and the power of his Spirit, and not in or by any of his good diſpoſitions.</p>
               <p>Let us in the holy feare of God looke to our lives, and never applaud our ſelves by our owne ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues. The whole world is
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:1458:115"/>guilty of a ſinne it hath no ſenſe or feeling of, and even the beſt are in worſt caſe: let the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> come to triall, and by a conviction more than le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall, ſee what the Goſpel re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proveth, let them thus rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon with themſelves; It is too groſſe and ſottiſh to ſay I am a ſinner, I am worſe, I am an Infidell and wrapped up in the worlds condemnation. It is high time for my ſoule to bee dealt withall, and that by a more powerfull cauſe than the morrall Law or mine owne conſcience: I muſt to the Goſpel and conviction of Gods Spirit, and never reſt till I finde the Spirit preſent and come home to my heart.</p>
               <pb n="156" facs="tcp:1458:116"/>
               <p>I ſhall afterwards intreat of all the heads of this firſt conviction. I will firſt o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen the ſinne: ſecondly, who are guilty of it. Thirdly, how they muſt be dealt withall. Fourthly, by whom. Fiftly, in what manner. The ſame methode ſhall be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved in both the other convictions, that by the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance in my Text of the Iewes diſobedience and judgement, we may learne to tremble and feare to live either without Evangelicall faith, Evangelicall righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, or Evangelicall judgement.</p>
               <p>Three things in the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel inſeparably lincked to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether: He that beleeves in Chriſt, hath righteouſneſſe
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:1458:116"/>imputed; and hee that hath righteouſneſſe imputed, hath holineſſe infuſed to reject Satan and his ſervice, and receive the true judgement of the Spirit to bee at his command and Kingly go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment. I ſhall wiſh eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry head propounded, may have it's uſe and applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 1. Let the want of faith in Chriſt, and righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe from him, and an holy ſubjection to Gods Spirit, more perplex us than all earthly wants. Let ſuch eſpecially as are profane thinke of it, who beſide the burden of the Law groſly abuſed, have the Goſpel to beat home their condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and beare them downe
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:1458:117"/>headlong to hell for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of great ſalvation ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred them in their ſinnes. But eſpecially let the more morall men marke them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, &amp; if they were as for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward as <hi>Paul</hi> to know none, or little evill by themſelves, yet to thinke they are not ſo juſtified: but the Goſpel can bring upon them a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter condemnation than the Law, and challenge them for more than ever was drea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med of by their owne ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count and reckoning by the Law. Laſtly, let carnall Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pellers deſcend and ſee their preſumption, that will bee ſure of faith without con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viction. They ſuppoſe it is ſoone gotten and loſt, and that to play at faſt and looſe
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:1458:117"/>with God, is no danger. They will have faith when they liſt, and eaſie convicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons leade them any wayes. It is time for them to learne a better leſſon, and to bee ſoundly laſhed from our Text, that the convictions of Gods Spirit are no eaſie and morall perſwaſions fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to our inclination, but ſound convictions taking from us all excuſes, be they never ſo witty, and laying us low before God to be dealt withall at his pleaſure.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Vſe</hi> 2. Theſe wants are common as well as dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous; thouſands dye and are never ſenſible of any hurt this way. The world is to be dealt withall to take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice that theſe wants are
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:1458:118"/>the greateſt poverty of it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 3. It is pitty the danger being ſo great and ſo common, but that Miniſters ſhould faithfully preach and convince theſe ſinnes before all others. Sinnes of the Law light more clearely upon mens conſciences, but theſe ſinnes finde conſcience not onely aſleepe, but liveleſſe, as never ſtirring in any thoughts that ſuch evils lie at the doore, more to watch vs with damnation than any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Vſe</hi> 4. There is no prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching or meanes effectuall but that is accompanied by the Spirit. There is a diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence between Preachers, as there is betweene an Infant and Gyant, drawing the
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:1458:118"/>ſame Bow. Yet the Arrow of a Gyant ſhot againſt the ſtone wall, pierceth not, but reboundeth backe againe with the greater violence. So the moſt happy and dex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trous Preacher, flocked after for his gifts, may ſhoot as unprofitably as a weaker Teacher; his arrowes and errands to the ſoule ſpeed no better for the hardneſſe of it, than if hee had never loſt his labour, or ſpent his ſtrength in vaine upon ſo ſtubborne ſpirits. Chriſt and all his Apoſtles were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted by the unbeleeving <hi>Iewes:</hi> their ſtiffe neckes would never bend to the yoake of the Goſpel, or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>circumciſed hearts beleeve it.</p>
               <pb n="162" facs="tcp:1458:119"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</hi> 5. Muſt bee for true triall and examination of our ſelves, whether the Spirit be come and hath convin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced us to give over all oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, and yeeld to live by a new principle, reſt upon a new righteouſneſſe, and be ruled by a new Law. I ſhall give the tryall in my further ſearch unto this Conviction. <hi>Luthers</hi> three Schoole ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters have helped me in theſe thoughts. Afflictions and accuſations have ſet prayer on worke, and both have put forth Meditations. Hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble repentance, ſaid that worthy Chancellour of <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris,</hi> is the firſt ſtaire of the Ladder of Contemplation. I will not complaine of my wrongs, yet if they had ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:1458:119"/>beene, thou mightſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver have had my thoughts ſo legible. I thanke God, I never found the hands of Authority ſo ready to ſmite, as evill tongues to accuſe.</p>
               <p>1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.17.18. <hi>What ſhall be the end of them that obey not the Goſpel of God? Where ſhall the ungodly and ſinner appeare?</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The great ſinne and endleſſe ſorrow of Gods houſhold Enemies.</head>
               <p>HAving diſcharged my ſelfe of the firſt part, concerning the ſharpe and ſtrict government of Gods Familie, I come to the ſhar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſt and ſevereſt of his
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:1458:120"/>judgements upon their ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies. <hi>Peter</hi> inſtanceth in the <hi>Iewes,</hi> for to them he writes both his Epiſtles, and in both hee aimes at three things; 1 the conſolation of beleevers; 2 the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction and juſt puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of their enemies. 3 the future promiſes made to the Nation of the <hi>Iewes</hi> at the comming of Chriſt. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leevers had ſtrong trials when S. <hi>Peter</hi> writ his Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, and even their owne Nation was worſt to their profeſſion. This Nation Chriſt threatens with an end, and Saint <hi>Peter</hi> now ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies it, and by the accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhment of ſignes, gives aſſurance that it is now at hand. Iudgements are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:1458:120"/>at his owne houſe and familie, and therefore will end ſuddenly upon their enemies. This was the yeare when <hi>Nero</hi> made Bone-fires of the bodies of Chriſtians, and to extin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh the ignominie of his owne ſetting <hi>Rome</hi> on fire, fireth Chriſtians as Faggots, and makes their flames to give light the whole night. This is the fiery tryall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leevers are told of, <hi>verſe</hi> 12. and deſerves to begin the firſt perſecution. It ſhall not be long before it bring an end upon the <hi>Iewes</hi> and their Nation, for obſtinacy and cruelty to their bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren. It is ſuppoſed Saint <hi>Peter</hi> and Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſuffered in this firſt fiery tryall.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="166" facs="tcp:1458:121"/>
               <head>Their ſinne and diſobedience.</head>
               <p>They are taxed in this Text for the violation both of Law and Goſpel, neither Iuſtice nor Mercy affect them. They diſobey the Goſpell, and againſt the Law they are found guilty both of impiety and uncha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritableneſſe. They are caſt in both Courts. In the Court of Iuſtice they are here arraigned for ungodly perſons under the charge of the firſt Table, and ſinners and unrighteous under the charge of the ſecond Table. In the Court of Mercy, they are branded with the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, as a rule diſobeyed, and a remedy deſpiſed. Iuſtice might be pacified by Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy,
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:1458:121"/>and the Law taken off by the Goſpel: but theſe faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe and feareleſſe wretches care neither for rule nor re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medie. They neither are mindfull of that which is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them in the Law, or might doe them good in the Goſpel.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the Goſpel ſinnes.</head>
               <p>To diſobey the Goſpell is by Saint <hi>Iohn, Chap.</hi> 16.8. ſummoned up in three par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars; Firſt, in the want of faith. Secondly, in the want of righteouſneſſe. Thirdly, in the want of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe. The diſobedient <hi>Iewes</hi> found no want of faith in Chriſt. They ſuppoſed they were full of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in themſelves, and
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:1458:122"/>that they wanted no ſpirit of grace to diſplace Satan in his government, and ſet up the government of Chriſt in their hearts. I will from the inſtance and example in large my ſelfe in laying to the charge of the whole world this Goſpell-ſinne here applyed to the <hi>Iewes,</hi> and by way of warrantable explication follow S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Iohn</hi> as a Commentary upon Saint <hi>Peter.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Three Goſpel Controverſies.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iohn</hi> 16.8. And when he is come, <hi>Hee will convince the world of ſinne, and of righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, and of judgement.</hi> Here lie three great Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſies betweene God and the whole world. Firſt,
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:1458:122"/>what that ſinne is which the world counts no ſin. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, what that righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe is w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> in the eſteem of the world is no righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. Thirdly, what that judgment is that the world reputes for no judgement. There is a Law from God, and conſcience in man, that tels the world of many ſinnes that it yeelds unto, that gives information of righteouſneſſe applauded in the vertues and actions of men; and it takes from both a forme of judgement and government, that for it owne ſafety it allowes and likes well of: but alas, in theſe three there is neither Law nor conſcience to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme us; nay, to both they
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:1458:123"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="173" facs="tcp:1458:123"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="170" facs="tcp:1458:124"/>are ridiculous, conceiving nothing reaſonable in all theſe, but that which is mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall and naturall to our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition in the ſtate of inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency, and remainders ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of in our corrupted na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. <hi>Adam</hi> in <hi>Paradiſe</hi> was not apprehenſive of theſe diſputes, neither were ſuch doctrines agreeable to his inſight. Theſe are for new creatures, conquered and convinced by Gods Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The unknowne Sinne.</head>
               <p>All the world is ignorant of faith, and would ſo periſh but for the Goſpel. It was not the Law (the <hi>Iewes</hi> ſo much inſiſted upon) y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> could reach or reſolve their rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:1458:124"/>in diſcovery of this ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret; and becauſe they would know no more than <hi>Moſes</hi> Law, they periſhed in this ſinne. This finne is expoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to be want of faith in Chriſt, <hi>verſe</hi> 9. It is either the root or ſigne of all other ſinnes. He that wants faith in Chriſt is diſcharged of no ſinne. Convince him of this, and convince him of all.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>How great a ſinne it is?</head>
               <p>Want of faith in Chriſt is of all ſinnes the greateſt. it denies the mercy of God, and makes a man the murtherer of himſelfe. It tals for Iuſtice, and refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth a pardon. It convinceth of ſin, and rejects the reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy.
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:1458:125"/>It caſts a man into the jawes of death, and cares not for helpe or hand that ſhould pull him out. <hi>Moſes</hi> Law is not without puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but this without eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cape. If the Goſpel deny us mercie, our miſery is irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coverable.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The neglect.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.2, 3. The Law of <hi>Moſes</hi> in every tranſgreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and diſobedience, is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>payed with recompence and reward. All the benefite is that an eſcape is granted from the rigour of this Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice: but if we neglect the great ſalvation of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, we have no way to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voyd vengeance and wrath to come. Loſe the oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:1458:125"/>of the Goſpel, and all is loſt. Wee may recover the loſſes of the Law, but if we looke not to the Goſpel, our caſe will bee deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Contempt.</head>
               <p>There is no mercie, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.28. to the deſpiſer of <hi>Moſes</hi> Law; and yet <hi>ver.</hi> 29. there is ſorer puniſhment to him that deſpiteth the Spirit of grace, ſpeaking in the Goſpel. No mercy is the hight of miſery, and yet <hi>Moſes</hi> Law cannot be ſtrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned ſo high, as to deny all mercy. It may inflict death, but the Goſpel may take off the eternall puniſhment thereof: but alas, if the Goſpell be abuſed, and mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:1458:126"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="171" facs="tcp:1458:126"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="172" facs="tcp:1458:127"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="173" facs="tcp:1458:127"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="174" facs="tcp:1458:128"/>denyed, what Law ſhall remove that curſe, and bee able to releaſe the ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner?</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Evangelicall Apoſtacy.</head>
               <p>We are all fallen in the firſt man, and are for our Apoſtacy to be loathed and left of God without pittie: But the Lord dealt not ſo with us for our ſinnes. He had mercy upon us, in the Mediatour, and made him a meanes to reconcile us a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, and bring us into fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour: but reade with trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling (all Apoſtataes fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Goſpell) and ſee with hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour your dreadfull, doome, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.38. <hi>If any draw backe, my ſoule ſhall have no pleaſure in him.</hi> Woe unto
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:1458:128"/>us if ſuch words had beene uttered againſt us for our Apoſtacy in <hi>Adam.</hi> The Lord never ſet his ſoule againſt us, but even with it pittied us and pardoned us graciouſly: but now to A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtatize and forſake his mercy, his very heart riſeth againſt us, and we are moſt loathſome and abominable in his eyes. Hee abhorres for ever to caſt a favourable looke upon us, or once to vouchſafe us acceptation againe. Chriſtian Apoſtataes are the worſt of men, and ſhall have wages with the greateſt vengeance. <hi>Matth.</hi> 12.31, 32. Blaſphemie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Goſpell cannot be forgiven: All legall blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemie is pardonable, the
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:1458:129"/>Father pardoneth it againſt himſelfe, the Sonne will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit it for his part: but if it proceed to touch the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, it paſſeth all mediation. I will not bee peremptory, and yet I preſume never any man committed this ſinne againſt the Law. I conceive it onely to be a Goſpel-ſinne that will ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit of no pardon in the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection of mercy. The <hi>Iewes</hi> committed this ſinne in the Scribes and Phariſees, and I feare all this rabble here condemned in <hi>Peter,</hi> were not farre from it, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving had the Goſpell ſo long continued, and ſo vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently and wilfully oppoſed. It is enough that I have tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched it as the height of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedience
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:1458:129"/>againſt the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, and have wiſhed men to take warning of this woe and wickedneſſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Evangelicall deſpaire.</head>
               <p>The preparation of the Law, is to bring the ſinner to deſpaire in himſelfe and all worldly helpe, and ſo is a meanes to bring him to Chriſt: but Evangelicall deſpaire of mercy after the meanes of the Goſpell offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and contemned, is dead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and dangerous, and few ever went out of it. Men lie long under the ſenſe of their owne miſery without comfort: but they may with confidence wait and expect to the laſt, and reſt in hope they ſhall not alwayes bee
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:1458:130"/>denyed their ſuites and ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plications. Onely deſperate contemners of the Goſpell when they fall into ſome extraordinary judgement of God, and the horror of their owne conſciences, are little better than Devils, waiting for the damnation and ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter perdition of their ſoules. Satan will be ſure to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade men <hi>firſt</hi> that God will not puniſh, and then that GOD will not par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The world is guilty of this ſinne.</head>
               <p>Want of faith in Chriſt is as common as it is dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous; for Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> ſtickes not to charge all the world with it, and truely either in
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:1458:130"/>the penalty or the ſinne, wee may judge no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> exempted. Where the Goſpel is not preached, it is the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of their firſt rebellion. God is not tyed to give faith to any, or to affoord him his Goſpell. Theſe mercies are tranſcendent, and of no mutuall right be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene God and his crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. The Goſpell was preached in Paradiſe, but <hi>Adam</hi> had no Covenant that it ſhould be hereditary, and follow him and all his poſterity. The Law was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tailed, but the Goſpell is the free bleſſing of Almighty God.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="180" facs="tcp:1458:131"/>
               <head>Want of faith, the penalty and puniſhment of all Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinde.</head>
               <p>Faith in a Mediatour, and faith in God, are of a large difference. The Law in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding, threatning promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, is to be beleeved, and the want of this faith brought <hi>Adam</hi> into ſinne, and it is the roote of all ſin, and deſerver of all judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. What GOD com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, that the creature muſt beleeve to be his duty; what he threatneth he muſt in faith and feare yeeld unto, and what he promiſeth, hee muſt likewiſe with the ſame faith imbrace. Now this faith is an affection or rather a piece of Gods I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage,
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:1458:131"/>framing the affectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s in a conformable power to all Gods co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mands, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>minations &amp; promiſes: but Evangelicall faith is no part or piece of the created image of God: but a new principle put into the ſoule in place of origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall righteouſneſſe to bring forth actuall obedience, both in the inward and outward man. The want of this faith (as I ſaid before) is not the root of all ſinne, for where there is no Goſpel, the want of this faith will never bee imputed for a ſinne. The want of that other, is truely and indeed the root of all ſinne, and originall of all pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment. Not to beleeve in God was the ſinne of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam</hi> and all his poſterity.
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:1458:132"/>But want of beleeving in Chriſt, is not of the ſame extent. It is a ſigne that no ſin is diſcharged, &amp; we may ſafely ſay, it is the deſert of all men, for the want of the firſt faith to be deprived of this. Negative Infidelity condemnes no man for ſin; take away the meanes of Conviction, and the ſinne ceaſeth. <hi>Non poſitis medijs, &amp;c.</hi> Deny men the Goſpel, and free them of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel-ſinnes: but poſitive In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidelitie is a ſin, and where God affords his Goſpel hee lookes for obedience, and condemnes the contrary.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Want of faith the ſinne of the Church.</head>
               <p>To want faith where the
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:1458:132"/>Goſpel is preached, is an hainous and horrible ſinne; better ſuch men had never heard it, than that the ſound of it ſhould paſſe away without ſenſe and ſanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation. This is that, that truely makes the world guilty. Legall ſinne may binde us to the penalty, and want of faith in God may puniſh us with want of faith in Chriſt: But want of faith in Chriſt, in Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians and Profeſſors of the Goſpel, is a guilt above all guiltineſſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The worlds conviction by the Goſpel.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 15.22.24. The <hi>Iewes</hi> had been without the ſinne of the Goſpel, if by the
<pb n="184" facs="tcp:1458:133"/>Goſpel Chriſt had not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced them. This Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>victi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on takes away every cloake from ſinne, and leaves no co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering to caſt over a ſinner, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 9.41. If the <hi>Iewes</hi> had remained in their blindneſſe without the Goſpel, they had in compariſon beene without ſinne: but ſaying wee ſee better than thou canſt teach us, therefore Chriſt concludes againſt them that their ſinne remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, that is, their ſinne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Goſpel. But here comes in the great doubt and difficulty, what power have men to be convinced by the Goſpel, and how is God righteous in theſe Goſpel-puniſhments? I ſhall anſwer as followeth.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="185" facs="tcp:1458:133"/>
               <head>Mans capacitie of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viction.</head>
               <p>That man is capable of Evangelicall Conviction is by no man to bee denyed. Wee are not ſtockes and ſtones under the words of reproofe. We have under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandings and wils, and by the ſame created underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, I apprehend the Law, by the ſame I apprehend the Goſpel, and by the ſame will, I obey the one and the other: but theſe powers are too remote to remove the doubt, wee muſt not ſpeake of faculties, but their obedientiall and conforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble power to the Lawes gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven them by their Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="186" facs="tcp:1458:134"/>
               <head>Mans conformity to Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viction.</head>
               <p>God having made man the free beginner of his owne <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ctions, beſides the facultie of will and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, gave man originall righteouſneſſe, to further him in the production of actuall obedience, that if he pleaſed, hee might in all things conforme himſelfe to his Creators commands. If God had done no more for <hi>Adam</hi> than made him reaſonable and free, hee had wanted the obedientiall power, and had beene una<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to conforme himſelfe to the commands, commina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and promiſes of the Law; Therefore God to
<pb n="187" facs="tcp:1458:134"/>perfect his worke, added a further helpe needfull for obedience, in placing in man his owne Image, and printing upon his ſoule a perfect patterne of all that hee was to follow, and to imitate his Creator in. Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving loſt this Image, yet there ſtill remained ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent for conviction and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation: But we are now to try whether this will teach the Goſpel, of the law no queſtion is made.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of power to beleeve in Chriſt by creation.</head>
               <p>Many learned and godly Divines have aſſerted and aſſured us, that <hi>Adam</hi> in his innocency had power to beleeve in Chriſt. Of the ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacitie
<pb n="188" facs="tcp:1458:135"/>no man doubteth: but that will not ſolve the difficultie; for all the que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion lyeth upon the obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entiall and conformable power of <hi>Adam.</hi> This hee had not to the Law without originall righteouſneſſe, and I beleeve we ſhall be puz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to find it in <hi>Adam</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a new principle in the place of his firſt righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, being expulſed by ſinne. Without faith it ſelfe, I feare no man can con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme himſelfe to the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel; not that faith which was a part of Gods Image by creation: but that faith which is the principle of the life and obedience of the new man. Such a principle as never came within the
<pb n="189" facs="tcp:1458:135"/>kenne or cogniſance of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam,</hi> upon the beſt day of his creation and perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. I will preſſe but three arguments, and leave them to the anſwer of thoſe that are wedded to this opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The principle of life and Religion.</head>
               <p>No power is obedientiall and conformable to GOD without a principall, as well as inſtrumentall cauſes. The faculty is ſubſervient to the principall cauſe. It may livide from it, but without it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> cannot doe well. Man had reaſon and will to know and obey God, and to both was added by the Almighty, his owne Image
<pb n="188" facs="tcp:1458:136"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="189" facs="tcp:1458:136"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="190" facs="tcp:1458:137"/>or originall righteouſneſſe, that both reaſon might bee directed, and the will or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered to obey and ſerve him. Man had power to ſeparate his underſtanding from true knowledge, and his will from a holy and righteous impreſſion of Gods Image in ſpeciall up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it. He might refuſe to doe well, but to attaine that end without ſuch grace it was utterly impoſſible. The like muſt be underſtood of man in his lapſed eſtate, hee is not deprived of will and underſtanding: yet ſuch faculties are not ſufficient without faith infuſed, that may as a principle helpe us to action and pleaſing of God. Not faith in God, for
<pb n="191" facs="tcp:1458:137"/>that turnes the minde to le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall obedience: but faith in Chriſt, which ſerves us to obey Evangelically: contrary principles cannot produce the ſame effect, or bring to the ſame end; we cannot by the ſame faith live in Chriſt, and live in our ſelves.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Contrariety of commands.</head>
               <p>There is no obedientiall power that can yeeld at the ſame time to doe contrary things. The Law commands us to <hi>doe and live,</hi> the Goſpel to <hi>beleeve and live.</hi> He that muſt conforme to the one, cannot by the ſame power immediately conforme to the other. Whiles <hi>Adam</hi> ſtands bound to the Law for life, hee cannot ſtand
<pb n="192" facs="tcp:1458:138"/>bound to the Goſpel for the ſame. It is impoſſible for any man to have power (in beleeving his duty is) to bee ſaved by his workes, and at the ſame time to bee ſaved by faith. It were a ſtrange ſubjection to command the creature to live by his deeds, and then at the ſame time to croſſe it, and ſay, not ſo, but by the ſame power, <hi>Beleeve and thou ſhalt be ſaued.</hi> Such teaching we may ſuſpect, and ſeeke for better ſatisfaction by ſome more reaſonable, faire and even reſolution; for in truth this is rather ſubverſion than ſubjection of will and power.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="193" facs="tcp:1458:138"/>
               <head>A power needleſſe and needfull.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Adam</hi> in the eſtate of innocency, had no need of faith in Chriſt, and then <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e give him power to beleeve in him: Man fallen, hath need and neceſſary uſe both of power and faith, and then hee hath loſt both. Poore creature, God abounds in goodneſſe, when thou haſt no neede of his helpe, and forſakes thee in the extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity and greateſt neceſſity. Are theſe the waies of Gods wiſedome, to be laviſh of power where man hath no need, and to leave him where his helpe is of uſe: no certainely, God does no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in vaine, but gives
<pb n="194" facs="tcp:1458:139"/>man what is uſefull, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves himſelfe to give more when, where, and to whom he pleaſeth.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A power to beleeve in Chriſt by Redemption.</head>
               <p>Faith is the free gift of God. It was neceſſary by creation that man ſhould not want the ſanctified affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of faith to beleeve in the Creatour. It was <hi>debi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum naturae,</hi> Natures debt to ingage God to make his creature holy and righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous: but now it is of grace to give him the new prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple of life to fetch from Chriſt both righteouſneſſe and holineſſe for the whole man. Heere is nothing he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reditary or naturall, the
<pb n="195" facs="tcp:1458:139"/>Goſpel is free when, where, &amp; to whom to beſtow it. It was given in Par<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>diſe to all the ſonnes of men, yet deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cended not by propagation from fathers to children. <hi>Adam</hi> might have propa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gated originall righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, as well as originall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>inne. But be neither pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagates Evangelicall faith, or the want of it to his po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity. It is perſonall both in the habite and privation. No man is ſaved but by his owne faith, or condemned but by his owne infidelity. The want of faith in Chriſt is every mans proper ſinne, and can be imputed to none without the Goſpel. Wee make it the Churches ſinne, and not of all the world.</p>
               <pb n="194" facs="tcp:1458:140"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="195" facs="tcp:1458:140"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="194" facs="tcp:1458:141"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="195" facs="tcp:1458:141"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="196" facs="tcp:1458:142"/>
               <head>Gods preparation and donati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of faith.</head>
               <p>Leaving the power of Mans innocency, and vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſall freedome to beleeve legally or Evangellically, wee fall into the ſafe way, and ſay, that whereſoe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> the Goſpel is preached, God gives or is prepared to give faith in Chriſt. Hee mockes no man, but is ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous in the ſalvation of eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſoule, to which the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel is ſent. Every hearer in the Church is zealouſly perſwaded to repent. The Miniſters minde and Gods meet in his holy ordinances, and the Word is earneſtly ſpoken to every eare. God himſelfe goes with his meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage
<pb n="197" facs="tcp:1458:142"/>from ſeate to ſeate, and from man to man, with true and hearty deſire of his converſion; yet notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding he gives not equall grace to all, as ſhall appeare in our diſtribution there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The donation of faith.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 13.48. <hi>As many as were ordained to eternal life, beloved.</hi> To the Elect hee gives faith. He is not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly prepared to preach unto them his Goſpell, but hee prepares their hearts to receive it. He gives unto his choſen ones, the bleſſed Goſpel of peace and recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciliation, and hee gives them faith to beleeve it. We have all the ſame capacity:
<pb n="198" facs="tcp:1458:143"/>but not the ſame conformi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. Our powers are alike in underſtanding and will: but that obedientiall and fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liall ſubjection to God and his Goſpel is peculiar to ſome.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>God is prepared to give faith to all that heare his Goſpel.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 23.37. <hi>I would, yee would not.</hi> It is the will of God by the Goſpel that all ſhould be gathered unto him. Mans will reſiſteth Gods will, and makes that Goſpel of none effect that ſhould be effectuall unto all. God may adde further grace and give men hearts to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive as freely, as his Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell is offered unto them:
<pb n="199" facs="tcp:1458:143"/>but ſuch grace is a royall prerogative, and reſerved for ſome of many. All are beholding to God, but ſome finde and feele the very ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of his grace, and are never able to be thankefull enough, that they above others ſhould receive ſo much.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the righteouſneſſe of God.</head>
               <p>To require performance, and give no power, is as un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>equall in the command to al, as it is in the gift to ſome. To ſeeke where hee ſowes not, and to reape without labour is unreaſonable, if not unrighteous. Man ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver had power to obey, and therefore a heavy and harſh
<pb n="200" facs="tcp:1458:144"/>command is impoſed upon him.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Mans power to obey the Goſpel</head>
               <p>There is never a man but is guilty of that power that God hath given him, and does leſſe than he is inabled by his owne freedome. There is no man, but he may frequent the meanes, and come to the place of Gods worſhip. Secondly, being come, hee hath eares to heare. Thirdly, he hath an underſtanding to know the logicke and language of the holy Ghoſt. Fourthly, by that knowledge to come to an hiſtoricall faith. Fiftly, to affect, reverence and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard both Miniſters and
<pb n="201" facs="tcp:1458:144"/>meſſage. Sixtly, to bring forth ſome fruits. Seventh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, to attend and wait daily for the regenerating Spirit, that may convert and turne him truely unto God. This power man uſeth not, and is juſtly condemned for the abuſe of it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Want of faith in Chriſt ſimply no ſinne.</head>
               <p>If condemnation were abſolutely and originally from faith, a power were neceſſary to beleeve: but in divers caſes faith is found to be no ſinne in the want of it. <hi>Adam</hi> in the eſtate of innocency, had no faith in Chriſt as a Mediatour, and was blameleſſe, becauſe no Law injoyned it. Secondly,
<pb n="202" facs="tcp:1458:145"/>men that need this faith and yet want the Goſpell to convince them, are guiltleſſe of the ſinne, though in ſome ſenſe they may bee ſaid to bee guilty of the puniſhment. Every curſe and want of favour be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing due to every ſonne of <hi>Adam.</hi> It therefore remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth that they onely are to be taxed that have the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Sinnes of the Goſpell are ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gravations of the Law.</head>
               <p>It muſt bee preſuppoſed that a man is guilty of ſinne and death before the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell charge him with a greater meaſure of evill, and make him worſe both in ſinnes and ſorrowes. It
<pb n="203" facs="tcp:1458:145"/>is not the want of faith barely that turnes a man in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to hell; for finde payment in thy ſelfe, and ſatisfaction to the Law, and God will challenge thee no further: but that is impoſſible, and therefore the Law caſts the firſt ſtone at thee, and beares thee over with the blow of death; then comes the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel and buries thee under that ſtone without all hope of mercy. A man is blind and rejects a cure: his wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe hath made him the worſe and more worthy of greater woes: ſo the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell tenders thee a pardon, thou contemnes it, and for contempt deſerves the ſorer puniſhment. It is not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore neceſſary for God to
<pb n="204" facs="tcp:1458:146"/>give every man power to be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eeve, but it is neceſſary for every man to be care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full he abuſe not the power he hath, and ſo double his terments and puniſhments in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Conviction is the worke of the Spirit.</head>
               <p>The Father gives over the adminiſtration to his Sonne, the Sonne to the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and he is the firſt that argueth and diſputeth with men of mercy and ſalvation. In his hands is now the kingdome of the Father and the ſonne, and this king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome is <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>reg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gum violentiae,</hi> the Kingdome that ſuffereth violence, <hi>Mat.</hi> 11.12, 13. <hi>Luke</hi> 16.16. In
<pb n="205" facs="tcp:1458:146"/>this kingdome, the Saints in ſuffering are more than conquerors, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.37. This is more than ever any Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour could utter, who have gained and kept their conqueſts with hardneſſe and hazzard. <hi>Matth.</hi> 28.18, 19. the power of Chriſt is to preach and proclaim that he will take his power, and reigne in and over all men. He is mercifull in giving warning before the execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and leaving his Spirit to make preparation for his kingdome, which ſhall bee <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> a kingdome of power, <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.17. ruling and over-ruling all the world. Chriſt having en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the ſubjection of the world ſhall give over his
<pb n="206" facs="tcp:1458:147"/>kingdome to his Father, which is <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.24. O the divine ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration of the Trinity! The Father the firſt perſon, paſſeth all to the Sonne, the Sonne makes it deſcend a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine to the holy Ghoſt. The ſame is the order of regreſſion, that was in the progreſſion, as formerly we have declared. The holy Ghoſt the firſt poſſeſſour of the kingdome returnes it into the poſſeſſion of the Sonne, and the Sonne leaves it in the hands of his Father where he firſt had it, that he may <hi>be all in all.</hi> From him was the proceeding, and by good reaſon it muſt be to him againe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="207" facs="tcp:1458:147"/>
               <head>The comming of the Holy Ghoſt.</head>
               <p>The Goſpel convinceth no man in the abſence of the Spirit. Wee muſt pray in hearing of the Word, Come holy Spirit and viſit our hearts, bring home the convictions of Grace, that we may not with theſe ſtubborne <hi>Iewes</hi> diſobey thy Goſpel, and bring upon us and our habitations, their end and miſery. And thus much of their firſt ſinne, I will ſpeed on in the reſt, and ſpend leſſe time in my diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe. It was needfull to beate this ſinne home, and make the greater ſtay, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the greater ſtirre hath beene made about it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="208" facs="tcp:1458:148"/>
               <head>The denyall of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</head>
               <p>Morrall and civill men never knew the meaning of Evangelicall and Chriſtian righteouſneſſe. What Law acknowledgeth a man juſt by another mans juſtice, or wiſe by another mans wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome? Papiſts deride it, and the world hath not lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned how to conceive of it. It is a great ſinne to live in this ignorance, and an aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance to a man, hee wants wiſedome to know his own juſtification. Hee reſts in hope he is righteous, and wanting the knowledge of Chriſt, periſheth in his own pride and preſumption. Chriſt is both righteous in
<pb n="209" facs="tcp:1458:148"/>himſelfe and for us, and ſo is no man in the world.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A world of unrighteous men.</head>
               <p>We have a world of wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked men that are deſtitute of common honeſty: but if we adde to them even ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther world of honeſt men, that know no more than good neighbourhood, what a vaſt heape and confuſion have we of men and wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men unrighteous before God, and deſtitute of Ieſus Chriſt? A world is heere condemned for want of righteouſneſſe: and alas how did the blinde <hi>Iewes</hi> oppoſe this righteouſneſſe, and ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing themſelves juſt by another Law than the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel,
<pb n="210" facs="tcp:1458:149"/>are now frying in hell for their diſobedience.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Conviction of righteouſneſſe.</head>
               <p>It is pitty the world ſhould periſh without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proofe of this ſinne. It is that which Chriſt and all his Apoſtles laboured to bring the <hi>Iewes</hi> unto. They condemned Chriſt for a ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lefactour, and by his reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection and aſcenſion hee prooved plaine that he was both juſt and the juſtifier of ſinners. Here is ſtrong con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viction by reaſon and force of argument. No man can goe to God the Father that is unrighteous. There is no acceptation of ſuch into heaven. Now I have many witneſſes (ſaith Chriſt) of
<pb n="211" facs="tcp:1458:149"/>my aſcenſion. You ſhall ſee me aſcend, and ſee mee no more upon earth. You are my faithfull ones, to you I make demonſtration of my righteouſneſſe, that you may demonſtrate the ſame to others.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The office of the Spirit in this conviction.</head>
               <p>The world lies in ſinne and is held by Satan in ſtrong condemnation. It was a lie at the firſt that murthered himſelfe and all mankind, <hi>Iohn</hi> 8.44. Hee ſtood not in the truth, it was that which he oppoſed from the beginning. Firſt, by a queſtion, <hi>Hath God ſaid, &amp;c.</hi> Secondly, by a contradiction, <hi>Yee ſhall not
<pb n="212" facs="tcp:1458:150"/>dye at all, &amp;c.</hi> Thirdly, by diſputation, <hi>God knowes,</hi> and yee may know, that to eate and feare no death, will make you wiſe and worthy to be like God himſelfe, &amp;c. Thus was man murthered and by a lye deluded of his happineſſe, and became a lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer of that righteouſneſſe that God imprinted in his ſoule, when he firſt breathed it into his body. This loſſe can never be repaired by another of the ſame ſtampe; and therefore the Spirit of God beginning with feare to put a man beſide him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe and his own preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, openeth unto him his bondage and baſeneſſe in ſinne, and from the very bottome of hell recovereth
<pb n="213" facs="tcp:1458:150"/>him by the righteouſneſſe of Chriſt, and puts into him a more ingenuous Spirit to looke up to God in Chriſt and call him Father, and by adoption and grace to finde himſelfe the childe of God, heire of righteouſneſſe, and inheritour of the Kingdome of God, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.15.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>His comming for this end.</head>
               <p>The great Doctour CHRIST IESVS ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting himſelfe, ſends ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to be preſent with us, both for counſell and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort. He counſelleth us to ſeeke the beſt righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and comforteth us with the fruition of it. Hee perſwades us to deny our ſelves, and make ſure to be
<pb n="214" facs="tcp:1458:151"/>found in Chriſt cloathed with his righteouſneſſe. I wonder not to ſee civill ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt men to wander naked of this cloathing in the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty ragges of their owne rotten righteouſneſſe; they have no better ſpirit, than the ſpirit of the world to teach them a morall leſſon, and to grow proud to ſee themſelves before their neighbours in the honour of their owne vertues. This is the applauſe the beſt men of the world ſeeke for, and reſt in it as their <hi>ſummu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> Such were the <hi>Phariſees</hi> &amp; the <hi>Iewes</hi> here in my text, that diſobeyed the Goſpel, becauſe they ſaw in their own thoughts, a better way of juſtification than Chriſt
<pb n="215" facs="tcp:1458:151"/>by his Spirit taught them. But all their ſuppoſed com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort is a poore and beggerly payment in the praiſe and applauſe of men, with their comming ſhort of heaven. I diſgrace not morality and civilitie in the world, I wiſh there were more of their ranke, ſo they reſted not in that righteouſneſſe, but rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched at an higher price, even the invaluable treaſure in Chriſt, willing in humility to let all goe for the gaine therof. Yet I muſt conclude againſt the underlings of moral honeſtie, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> all ſuch as are inferiours to them muſt needes come ſhort of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, becauſe they come ſhort of them, that by Chriſts verdict are before
<pb n="216" facs="tcp:1458:152"/>them. Now the beſt mora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſts come ſhort of heaven, and therefore muſt they needs come ſhort, that are left many leagues behinde them. Gaine the Spirit, and grace, that in holineſſe wee may exceed them all, as we ſhall doe in righteouſneſſe by Chriſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Want of judgement.</head>
               <p>This is the great ſinne of the world in advancing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Chriſt Satans ſove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignty and ſuperioritie. He reigneth, and ruleth the world, and is a ſpeciall ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my to Chriſts kingdome. Holineſſe is the companion of righteouſneſſe; we may not grow wanton, becauſe the grace of juſtification
<pb n="217" facs="tcp:1458:152"/>hath abounded. God hath not left us to our liberties, as if by the way of hell, wee might advance to heaven. Iudgement and ſpirituall government is appointed to order us in our wayes, and to waft us by ſafe conduct over the Sea of this world to our harbour and haven in heaven.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A world of people without grace and ſanctification.</head>
               <p>The ſubject that the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit is to ſeaſon, is the unſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vory world. Holineſſe is a by-word amongſt men, and deriſion hath baniſhed it by the conceit of preciſe and ſtrict walking with God. A Saint is the worlds ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctacle and a very gazing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtocke,
<pb n="218" facs="tcp:1458:153"/>as if hee were as much runne out of himſelfe and madde, as he is runne from the world and his merry company. But the wonder is in the world it ſelfe, wilde in wickedneſſe, and wretched in the hands of Satan. His judgement is followed, and government extolled in all places and perſons. Wee can but ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empt a few from being fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers of him, no more than Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> exempts the world from guilt in this place. Hee is plaine, and chargeth the world with the Divels government, and freeth none but by the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit from this miſery.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="219" facs="tcp:1458:153"/>
               <head>Conviction of the beſt go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment.</head>
               <p>The ſetting up of the Lord Ieſus in the hearts and ſoules of men, is the beſt Common-wealth. It was that the woman travailed for <hi>Rev.</hi> 12. She lives in the Pagan Empire, and is pained as much to make it a Chriſtian, as ſhe is pinched by it. The ſtrong argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of perſwaſion is, that Chriſt by his death and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection hath judged the prince of the world, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feated him of all judgement. He held a right in the world till Chriſt removed it. Hee is a Father of all that hee murthered by his lie in Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radiſe, and therefore chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lengeth
<pb n="220" facs="tcp:1458:154"/>a right in his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren. Chriſt to bee parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker with theſe children, takes their fleſh, and by death ſubdues the murthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer, and delivers them from bondage, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 2.14, 15. It is therefore good reaſon that the children ſhould be ſubject unto him, leave the lyer, and live in conformity to the new Law of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Spirits application of judgement.</head>
               <p>It is juſt, Satan ſhould bee expulſed and caſt out by Chriſt, and hee confeſſeth againſt blaſphemers, that his command over Divels was executed and effected by the Spirit, <hi>Matth.</hi> 12.28.29.
<pb n="221" facs="tcp:1458:154"/>He enters into the ſtrong mans houſe, and being ſtronger than hee, bindes him, and ſpoyles him of his poſſeſſion. Hee caſts downe in us the ſtrong holds of this adverſary, and brings us into ſubjection and obedience to Chriſt and his rule and regiment; and for this end alſo muſt the Spirit deſcend and dwell with us. Thus have we the ſinne of diſobeying the Goſpell in want of faith, righteouſneſſe and holineſſe, the uſe follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The worlds inſufficiency and danger.</head>
               <p>Firſt, I looke upon the world, and wonder at pride
<pb n="222" facs="tcp:1458:155"/>and arrogancie. Men nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther know their debt nor danger. They ſee not the charge of the Law, nor diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge of the Goſpel. They live as men ſet at liberty by their owne luſts. They looke up and feare no ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count: Faith they minde not, neither doe they feele or finde any want of it to get them a diſcharge. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſufficient to beleeve, and yet confident all is paid. Tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting they are righteous, and yet ſcorne to be beholding to any for juſtification. They will barter with God and by commutative juſtice give him as much as they receive. They pleade in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocencie, and yet im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleade holineſſe. They will
<pb n="223" facs="tcp:1458:155"/>be honeſt and yet hate ſince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity. But ſeeing the guilt is moſt where the Goſpel is preached, let vs ſee our pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſours, and pry into their ſufficiency. Many we have leſſe morrall than <hi>Turkes,</hi> and more ignorant than <hi>Heathens</hi> of their owne Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion. They heare the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, and underſtand nothing. Better theſe men had lived <hi>Turkes</hi> than Chriſtians in name, to incurre all the guilt of the Goſpel. O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers preſume they have faith, and never knew they wanted it. They were ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver acquainted with the conviction of Gods Spirit, whoſe office is firſt to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade men they want faith in Chriſt, before he worke
<pb n="224" facs="tcp:1458:156"/>it in them. They would loath be ſuch Infidels, as once to know or acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge the time when they beleeved not. Ever ſince they were borne they have had a good faith, and they hope they ſhall dye ſo. God helpe them by his Spirit to ſearch their deceitful hearts, and to change the time of their untimely beliefe, and learne to know that the firſt of convictions is to finde faith wanting in the heart. Either conviction of the wat muſt precede, or the gift will never follow: but this was touched before, though never too much.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Spirits ſufficiency.</head>
               <p>Second Vſe is to ſee how well Chriſt hath left us,
<pb n="225" facs="tcp:1458:156"/>not to an inſufficient and deficient Teacher: but to a compleate and perfect Doctour armed with all ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments of conviction, to bring us from infidelitie to faith, from condemnation to juſtification, and abſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion from all our ſinnes, from uncleanneſſe to holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and from the thral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Satan, to the liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of ſonnes. God bee bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed for his Spirit, haſten his kingdome that we may bee prepared for Chriſt to reigne and rule in us when hee deſtroyeth the world, and triumphantly having ended all his victories, hee may bring us bodies and ſoules to his Fathers houſe. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="226" facs="tcp:1458:157"/>
               <head>The Christians triall.</head>
               <p>Third Vſe. Diſobedience to the Goſpel is a fearefull ſinne, and brings a fearefull end: we may by degrees make ſure our ſafety, if wee ſearch and ſeeke to climbe to heaven by theſe ſtaires or ſtaves in <hi>Iacobs</hi> Ladder, <hi>Matth.</hi> 5.3. Firſt gaine <hi>po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verty of Spirit,</hi> labour to bee an indigent begger, Know thou haſt nothing but what muſt come from Chriſt. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, be <hi>ſenſible</hi> of thy po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertie, be no ſturdie begger that will not ſtoupe and ſtirre from his flaſhes and flouriſhes in a bold and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudent ſeeking, as if the giver were as much in his debt for the receit, as hee
<pb n="227" facs="tcp:1458:157"/>will be in the givers for the gift. <hi>Verſe</hi> 4. learne thou to mourne and to grieve that ever it was thy hard hap to fall into ſuch miſery as to incurre Gods diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, of all plagues the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt, greater than Hell it ſelfe. Mourne to have that taken off more than any judgement. Say not with <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> take away the plague of my Land, but the hardneſſe of my heart. Say with <hi>David,</hi> take away the treſpaſſe, and for the reſt, ſay no more but this, here I am, Lord, doe and deale with me as thou pleaſeth. Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, aſcend yet higher, and be poſſeſſed of <hi>a meeke ſpirit,</hi> even to the Lord, as well as to men. A man may mourn
<pb n="228" facs="tcp:1458:158"/>and remaine ſtubborne and unbroken, but <hi>verſe</hi> 5. bee thou bleſſed with a meeke and milde heart. Mourne till thou be meeked and tamed for the Lords uſe. Fourthly, raiſe up thy ſelfe to <hi>hunger and thirſt, verſe</hi> 6. even for that righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe that will ſatisfie thy meeke and mournefull ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit. Empty thy ſelfe firſt with ſorrow and ſubjection to Gods will, and then bee aſſured thou ſhalt be filled. Fiftly, bleſſe thy ſelfe with <hi>a mercifull heart</hi> to others. Say unto God, if thou hadſt mercy in ſtore, thou wouldſt beſtow it liberally; ſay thou art ſo eager for it, that it would doe thee good to ſee God, in denying it thee,
<pb n="229" facs="tcp:1458:158"/>to give it to others. It is that above all, thy hunger and thirſt is bent upon, and by the want of it thou knoweſt the worth, va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue and price of ſo rich a commoditie. Certainely it cannot be long before the Lord will reach mercy to thy heart that art ſo merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to others, and even fill all thy deſires, <hi>verſe</hi> 7. Sixt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, having obtained mercy to pardon all thy ſinnes and to juſtifie thy perſon, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get not the third convicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in ſtudying for holineſſe, gaine <hi>a pure heart,</hi> for that will bring thee ſtill nearer unto God, to ſee him in his Ordinances, in this world, and in his glory in the world to come, <hi>verſe</hi> 8.</p>
               <pb n="230" facs="tcp:1458:159"/>
               <p>Seventhly, being at peace with God, thy ſelfe become <hi>a peace-maker</hi> for others. Study that all may be parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers of thy peace, both with God and man, <hi>verſe</hi> 9. Eightly and laſtly, take in the laſt beatitude, and thinke thou haſt made no ill bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine to ſuffer perſecution for righteouſneſſe ſake. Thou thy ſelfe art at peace with heaven and earth, and deſireſt warre with no man. If they make warre with thee and falſely, ſmite thee with their tongues, be pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent and rejoyce, that hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven is and will be more pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitious and favourable unto thee than this vale of mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery. And ſo I end the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pels diſobedience, and come
<pb n="231" facs="tcp:1458:159"/>to the puniſhments, leaving the legall ſinnes untouched, which every mans conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence will touch without an interpretour. The <hi>Iewes</hi> were unbeleevers, that was their great ſinne: but their owne Law of which againſt the Goſpel, they made their boaſt, was tranſgreſſed in every branch.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The puniſhment of the Goſpell.</head>
               <p>Conſiſteth in an end in this world, miſery in the world to come, ignorance of that miſery, and ſhame unſupportable as you have heard. The unbeleeving <hi>Iewes</hi> are now within five yeares of their end, and yet I know not (ſaith <hi>Peter</hi>) what their end ſhall be. It
<pb n="232" facs="tcp:1458:160"/>were well with them, if their end here did end their torment hereafter: but I ſtand amazed and confoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to thinke what tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments wait upon them li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, dying, and dead, ſuch as they ſhall never bee able to know or underſtand. They ſhall never ſee their worſt, or what woe may further be laid upon them: yet ſo much ſhall they ſee and ſorrow for, as to bee confounded for ever, and not to know where to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare, or how to looke up to behold his face, whom they can neither avoyd or abide.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="223" facs="tcp:1458:160"/>
               <head>The temporall end of the Iewes.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 24.6.13.14. The end is thrice repeated and appyled to <hi>Iewes,</hi> as may appeare by the ſignes, <hi>v.</hi> 5. I came in my Fathers Name, and could not be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted. Others ſhall come in their owne, and bee graced of you with an <hi>us recipietis.</hi> But this will <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ell you roundly in both <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ares, of what you feared to loſe by mee and might have ſaved: The <hi>Romans</hi> will come and take away your kingdome <hi>verſe</hi> 6. No marvell rumours of warre riſe in all places for rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion: but theſe two ſignes will not bring the end, for others are to follow, theſe
<pb n="234" facs="tcp:1458:161"/>are but the <hi>beginnings of ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, v.</hi> 9. Perſecution begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning at Gods houſe, will bee another ſigne and ſure to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of an end upon Rebels, more againſt God than men. <hi>verſe</hi> 10. Apoſtacie will follow perſecution, and cold Chriſtians will ſoon ſhrinke with the firſt affronts of evill: but the promiſe is if any will ride out the ſtorme at a ſafe Anchor of hope, when the end comes, hee ſhall be ſaved and not pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh with Rebels. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>erſe</hi> 14. The departure of the Goſpel is another evidence of the end, <hi>Dan.</hi> 9.26. <hi>&amp; non ei,</hi> is a ſhort and ſharpe ſpeech, as abrupt for <hi>Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lems</hi> ruine as they ſenſe: To Meſſiah ſhall the <hi>Iewes</hi> be
<pb n="235" facs="tcp:1458:161"/>longer a people. <hi>Matth.</hi> 21.43. The kingdome goes in effect when the Goſpel de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parts, <hi>Dan.</hi> 9.27. One weeke is granted for the ſtay of it, that is, as before wee have delivered, ſeven yeeres, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning when Chriſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to preach to them, and ſo held on all his dayes, and three yeeres and an halfe af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, that is, from the thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tieth yeere of his Incarnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the 38. And in that yeere was the Commiſſion inlarged, <hi>Act.</hi> 10, 11, 12. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> a viſion and voyce from heaven aſſures <hi>Peter</hi> he may goe to <hi>Cornelius</hi> the <hi>Roman,</hi> and preach the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel. This viſion is allead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged often for confirmation of the paſſage of the Goſpel
<pb n="236" facs="tcp:1458:162"/>to the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> and is fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther confirmed by the gifts of the holy Ghoſt, beſtow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon them with the Goſpel. I take it for cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, that our Saviour in the related places, ſpake of no other end but this of the <hi>Iewes,</hi> which in foure things I will expreſſe as followeth. The hiſtory of their calamities upon earth, may be as an inſtance for all people to be warned by it, and take example of rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on againſt the Goſpel.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The loſſe of the Goſpel.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 21.43. The <hi>Iewes</hi> rejected the ſtone that God laid in <hi>Sion</hi> for ſalvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and all to reſt upon; for this rejection they are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected,
<pb n="237" facs="tcp:1458:162"/>and the firſt thing that removes from them is the Goſpel, and then fals the ſtone Chriſt heavy up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their Nation. They firſt ſtumble at it and ſtirre it by their ſtrength and rebellion, and then it rebounds upon them, and grinds them to powder, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 9.4.18. and 10, 22, 23. Divers removes before Gods glory depart, and enemies draw nearer.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The loſſe of their Kingdome.</head>
               <p>The Kingdome of God goes firſt, and then their Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion periſheth. The Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel moves from them ſlow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. Seven yeeres it ſtirres not though they ill deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved it. It begins with <hi>Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nelius</hi> in a private houſe,
<pb n="238" facs="tcp:1458:163"/>paſſeth more publikely to Cities and Regions of the <hi>Gentiles.</hi> God ſtill provo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the <hi>Iewes</hi> to recall it: but they rather perſecute it and all that profeſſe it; and therefore judgement and the end haſtned; and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in leſſe than the doubling of thirty eight yeeres the <hi>Iewes</hi> periſhed. In the firſt of the laſt of ſeventy yeeres Chriſt came, in the middle he died, and in the end deſtroyed <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem, Dan.</hi> 9.24. Seven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty weekes containe ſeven times ſeventy yeeres. Eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſeventy is famous, but the laſt excelleth all the reſt, as being the time of Chriſts birth, paſſion, and perdition of Rebels; but we repeate our former notes.
<pb n="239" facs="tcp:1458:163"/>The <hi>Iewes</hi> might have been wiſe out of <hi>Daniel,</hi> and dealt better for themſelves: but prophecies are of none effect to thoſe that are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouted to ruine.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Epiſtles to Iewes that give warning of this end.</head>
               <p>It is obſerved by a lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Divine, that I am to ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour with all reſpects of love and friendſhip (Maſter <hi>Ioſeph M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>de</hi>) that Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licall Epiſtles written to the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> expreſſe nothing of an end at hand: but rather upon miſtake of Epiſtles to the <hi>Hebrewes,</hi> give warning to the <hi>Gentiles</hi> of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2.2. I will by his directions point out ſome paſſages, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.37.
<pb n="240" facs="tcp:1458:164"/>The Apoſtle exhorteth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeving <hi>Iewes</hi> to patience, becauſe ſudden vengeance is ready to fall upon their enemies, the unbeleeving <hi>Iewes.</hi> Chriſt had threate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned their ruine, his long ſtay and lingring was tedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to fleſh and bloud, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially being tyred by trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles: <hi>Paul</hi> therefore cheeres up the hearts of the hearers with aſſurance Chriſt will not tarry long, but come quickely, and revenge his owne bloud and the bloud of his Saints upon that per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuting Nation. It ſhall glad our hearts to ſee Chriſt as good as his word in the ruine of <hi>Rome, Iames</hi> 5.7, 8. <hi>Be patient, &amp;c.</hi> The ſame exhortation, and the ſame
<pb n="241" facs="tcp:1458:164"/>argument, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.7. The like theame and diſputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, 1 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 2.18. Wee have an Advocate, &amp;c. and not wee onely that are <hi>Iewes:</hi> but alſo the whole world, &amp;c. the Epiſtle is generall, yet may have ſpeciall di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, and that to the <hi>Iewes</hi> in my apprehenſion. He tells <hi>them</hi> it is the <hi>laſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oure,</hi> for he lived to ſee it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the deſtruction of <hi>Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem,</hi> and gives one of Chriſts ſignes, <hi>Matth.</hi> 24.5. in falſe Chriſts flocked af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter by the <hi>Iewes.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The calamitie of the Iewes.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Dan.</hi> 12.1. <hi>Matth.</hi> 24.21. never greater, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.7. <hi>the end of all things,</hi> as if it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ad beene Doomeſday, as
<pb n="242" facs="tcp:1458:165"/>many underſtand <hi>Peter,</hi> who ſhould bee croſſe to Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2.2. ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept hee were thus under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood. I writ to you <hi>Iewes</hi> to be ſober and to watch unto prayer, for our Nation is ready to ſuffer and loſe all. Weepe and howle, <hi>Iam.</hi> 5.1. ye rich <hi>Iewes,</hi> for your miſeries ready to come upon you. You have but gathered your wealth for your enemies, and ſuch canker and ruſt of ſinne cleaves unto it, that it will witneſſe and worke againſt you. Your pleaſures, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits, preferments and wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonneſſe have fed and filled your hearts for the day of ſlaughter. You have killed the juſt without reſiſtance,
<pb n="243" facs="tcp:1458:165"/>but by their patience and your perſecution, you are now to periſh, and the Lord is nigh to execute the ſame upon you. I touch ſtill what I have taught before, becauſe I would be remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred, and made fruitfull to my Reader.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The loſſe of their lives and liberties.</head>
               <p>Never died people more deſperately, and the market they had made to ſell the bloud of Gods ſervants for nothing, is now made for them. The <hi>Romans</hi> buy theirs as cheape as ever they ſold Chriſts. Never Tragedy more lamentable; and if Ieſus Chriſt had not
<pb n="244" facs="tcp:1458:166"/>taken ſome pitty upon them, there had not beene left one piece of their fleſh untorne in pieces, <hi>Mat.</hi> 24.22. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther was captivity better than death, <hi>Ier.</hi> 22.10. That was never more verifyed tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> now, for to this day have they lived in their remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, as the moſt remarke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able wretches in the world. Let this end of the <hi>Iewes</hi> be our inſtruction and admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition, that we may be wiſe, and not periſh for the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of the Goſpel.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Their miſery in the world to come.</head>
               <p>The bloud of Chriſt pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſues them to Hell. It is not ſatisfied with the bloud in
<pb n="245" facs="tcp:1458:166"/>their bodies, but deſervedly makes them a prey to Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vels as well as men. It were an harſh cenſure to ſay they went all to Hell that periſhed by the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans.</hi> We will examine their caſe by Scripture, and a fearefull preſage thereof in the Revelation.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The eternall end of the Iewes.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 24.13. <hi>Hee that ſhall endure to the end, the ſame ſhall be ſaved.</hi> Men even amongſt you will apoſtatize and fall to the <hi>Iewes</hi> againe: but whoſoever ſhall hold out till their end come, ſhall not periſh with them; <hi>v.</hi> 15. Men are bidden reade with
<pb n="246" facs="tcp:1458:167"/>underſtanding: An Item ſet upon no other ſigne but this: When you ſee the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> Army placed in the Mount of Olives, eſcape for your lives. But how ſhall they eſcape when the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my lies in their way, and a watch againſt them on eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſide the City? I anſwer, God raiſed the firſt Army, and gave liberty to all that would reade and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, to be gone: and now went the Chriſtians to <hi>Pel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la,</hi> as I have ſhewed, this prophecie for their ſafety being ſeconded with a ſound from heaven, ſaying, <hi>Goe to Pella, goe to Pella.</hi> The promiſe is that Chriſtians ſound and ſincere in faith to the end, ſhall eſcape. Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory
<pb n="247" facs="tcp:1458:167"/>tels us they eſcaped: who then periſhes but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels to the Goſpel? The Text tels us, that the belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving <hi>Iewes</hi> had the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and that the end was for all thoſe that obeyed not the Goſpel. It give men leave to be charitable, but I deſire ſinne may have his due, and eſpecially Goſpel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinnes. Let men tremble that have a minde to treate more favourably of this end, and ſee what it is to call for the bloud of Chriſt to be upon them.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The preſage of their eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall woe.</head>
               <p>Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> lived to ſee it, and penned his Revelation
<pb n="246" facs="tcp:1458:168"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="247" facs="tcp:1458:168"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="248" facs="tcp:1458:169"/>after the deſtruction of the Citie. He alters the ſtyle of Hell, and gives it a name that no Prophet or Apoſtle did before him. Hee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves to be named that hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped me to this knowledge, Maſter <hi>Ioſeph Mede,</hi> whoſe praiſe, to Gods glory bee it ſpoken, I can never blazen too much. I ſhall recall what I quoted in one place for the ſtyle of Hell, <hi>Rev.</hi> 19, 20. The Lake of <hi>Sodome,</hi> or fire and Brimſtone. A new appellation of Hell up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this accident, as that judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious and induſtrious man relateth it. Multitudes of <hi>Iewes</hi> being met withall by the <hi>Romans,</hi> upon the banks of <hi>Iordan,</hi> are miſerably ſlaughtered, as formerly
<pb n="249" facs="tcp:1458:169"/>was touched, and their dead bodies buried in the River: But GOD will not ſuffer them there to reſt, but by the ſtrength of the ſtreame tumbles them from place to place, till hee plunge them into the Lake of Fire and Brimſtone for their buriall and graves. A ſad ſpectacle in my judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and no ſmall conje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture that their ſoules were buried in hell. Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> ſeemes to intimate ſo much to me. I will not bind any man to the ſtrict obſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of it, ſtill my deſire is to preſſe the puniſhment of diſobedience to the Goſpel. Such notes I am ſure thou mayeſt credite better than Popiſh legends and fables
<pb n="250" facs="tcp:1458:170"/>to make men feare hell, into which by Idolatry they teach them to leape, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver liſten after any legend or reading to prevent that. I will now wholly leave the inſtance of the <hi>Iewes,</hi> and teach all the miſery of Hell, in the lamentable ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremity of it, and extreame lamentation. <hi>Matthew</hi> 13.42. <hi>A furnace of fire,</hi> there is the lamentable ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremitie: <hi>wailing and gnaſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of teeth,</hi> there is extreame lamentation. The extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie we will expreſſe in foure termes; firſt, fire; ſecondly, darkeneſſe; third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, worme; fourthly, perdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="251" facs="tcp:1458:170"/>
               <head>The fire of Hell.</head>
               <p>Fire and water as they are of beſt uſe, ſo wee ſay of them, they are without mercy. It is their nature to doe what they doe: but it is the nature and property of God to have mercy, and therefore moſt unnaturall to be without mercie. It is juſt with God to change his mercy into juſtice, and kindle for the damned an unmercifull fire. Wee can quench our unmercifull fires with water: but in hell no water, no not a drop will bee allowed, not to quench, but not ſo much as to coole the heate of that flame upon the tippe of the
<pb n="252" facs="tcp:1458:171"/>tongue. The fire is a feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full extremity that nothing can allay it. Spirits are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gents too ſubtile to be pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents in our fire, they are more quicke in avoyding than that element can ſmite them. It hath beene much queſtioned by Schoolemen what we might deeme hell fire to be. If corporall, how ſhall it torment ſpirits and ſoules of men? If ſpirituall, how bodies and the fleſh of men? It were caſie to anſwer, by adding to fire the breath of the Almighty, who is able to extend or contract any creature to touch bodies or ſpirits with what torments he pleaſeth I had rather reſt in ſome lively example, than buſie
<pb n="253" facs="tcp:1458:171"/>my ſelfe with rules of uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainties. Our bleſſed Lord and Saviour is beſt able to tell us by experience, what fire that is that God kindles againſt ſinne, and with what extremitie it ſcorcheth and ſcourgeth the poore ſoule that muſt buckle and bend under it. I will preſent un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you, for an example, Ieſus Chriſt in the Garden, and upon the Croſſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Chriſts agony in the Garden.</head>
               <p>Feare and ſorrow begin his Paſſion. The objects that feare Chriſt, and worke him to ſorrow, are no eaſie ſcarcrowes and ſpectrums of men. Nay, all the Devils in hell are not able to put
<pb n="254" facs="tcp:1458:172"/>Chriſt into a Paſſion. To make him heavy in heart and ſoule, is no ſmall weight of woe; to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaine it preſſeth him to the very death, is a ſad ſymp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome of ſome ſevere and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakeable ſorrow. Paſſe we to his prayer, and ſee with ſubmiſſion how hee intreateth for the departure of it. Father, if there be any poſſible meanes to redeeme man without mee, and ſave me from the ſorrow I am in, let the bitter Cup eſcape my taſte. It is not a thing I ſue for once, but againe and againe I continue my fuite, and ſeeke more ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly than ever formerly in any prayer I expreſſed my ſelfe unto thee. It was
<pb n="255" facs="tcp:1458:172"/>no ſmall burden that Chriſt would have ſhifted from his ſhoulders, and ſetled up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſome other meanes and mediation. Hee will not ſhrinke to have man ſaved, but it would glad him to ſee himſelfe eaſed. If it be poſſible, my will is to bee eaſed: but thy will bee o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beyed, what ever I ſuffer. From ſorrow Chriſt fals to prayer, from prayer into an agony, and then he prayes more earneſtly as the bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den is increaſed. Now he ſweates and drops with bloud. It paſſeth through the veines, fleſh, skinne, not like ſome thinne dewie ſweat by an ordinary tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſudation, that Phyſitians diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe of for cauſe and cure:
<pb n="256" facs="tcp:1458:173"/>but it breakes violently out by great lumpes, and leapeth forcibly from his veines, and with a ſtrong current is caſt from them to his up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per garments, rumbling to the ground. To talke of diſeaſes when veines burſt, breake open their mouthes, or have their coates and containers thinned to ſweat out the bloud, is idle, to tell us of examples of the like, blaſphemous. Never was there ſickeneſſe, ſorrow, or example like this, meerely from apprehenſion and true conſideration of his owne ſufferings to be thus per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexed, no cauſe antecedent or conjunct, but what paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed betweene Chriſt our Saviour and Suretie, and his
<pb n="257" facs="tcp:1458:173"/>Father angry and diſpleaſed for our ſinnes. This firſt combate had beene enough to have annihilated or ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed up a meere creature, Angel or Man.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>His Paſſion upon his Croſſe.</head>
               <p>His preparation in the Garden brings him better armed to his Croſſe, he paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth by the wrongs of men and Angels: yet the one with the power of the hand, and the other with the hand of power, doe to him their worſt for divers houres. The power of darkeneſſe, after mans ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice was ended, laid at him, and left him not for many encounters. Hee that in the
<pb n="258" facs="tcp:1458:174"/>Wilderneſſe aſſaulted him thriſe, and often afterwards in the courſe of his life, brings now all the power of hell, and for his farewell to the world, hopes to have ſucceſſe in his and all our ruines and deſtructions. But theſe are light skermi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes and meane affronts to that which followed. All theſe are not worth the ſpeaking of he never opens his mouth to complaine of ſuch dealings and deeds of darkeneſſe, enough to plunge the beſt of us into hell: but after theſe troopes of wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe ſhaken off, he fals to the greateſt ſhocke and meetes with his match. His Father now takes him to taske, and turnes him to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other
<pb n="259" facs="tcp:1458:174"/>tune. He is compelled to cry out, and utter words of complaint, fearefull for deſpaire, if that word <hi>My Father,</hi> had not ſupported his faith; <hi>My God, my God, why haſt thou forſaken me?</hi> here is apprehenſion of dereli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction and deſertion, there is nothing that keepes Chriſt to God but faith. On his Fathers part he complaines of deſertion, on his owne he will not deſpaire, as long as God is his in application. The Father leaves; the Sonne cleaveth and claſpeth cloſe about him. Suppoſe the caſe had beene mans in either of theſe aſſaults; hee had upon the firſt appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion been, not onely diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayed, but confounded.
<pb n="260" facs="tcp:1458:175"/>Yet this would have put him into deſperation and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpaire for ever. He had not been able to liſpe one word of a better life, or laid the leaſt of his thoughts upon God. In ſtead of my God he would have blaſphemed and gnaſhed his teeth at his tormentor. Deare Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, dread this fire that fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtened upon the Innocent Sonne of God, and thinke what extremity it would be to you, but to touch the moſt utmoſt flame. Learne for ever to obey his Goſpel, and bee thankefull for his mercy and deliverance.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Viter darkeneſſe.</head>
               <p>The greateſt comfort of
<pb n="261" facs="tcp:1458:175"/>the fire is light, heate with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out it is an hell in our bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, and we ſee a burning Ague how it ſcorcheth us and ſends forth nothing but ſmoake and poyſon. It di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracts men with rage and madneſſe. Poore ſoules, we never felt ſuch a fire in the ſharpeſt Ague, as we ſhall find in our ſoules when hell fire entreth us, and we it. Vtter darkeneſſe is but a privation, yet the loſſe will make it a ſenſible torment. The Father of lights is God, that will bee gone. The Fountaine opened to us is Chriſt, but he will not vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite us. The light of Grace and Glory vaniſh with the Spirit. No inward or out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward light to comfort us
<pb n="262" facs="tcp:1458:176"/>will ſhew it ſelfe. Heaven and earth will curſe us, wee ſhall be blind in our ſelves, and burne without ſight of our owne miſeries. Senſe ſhall not be wanting, nor ſorrow to our ſenſes. Let darkeneſſe diſmay us to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obey, and let the light, whiles we have it, ſtirre us up to follow it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The never-dying Worme.</head>
               <p>The worme that gnawes upon the living man, and eates him up being dead, may both be killed and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed with us: but this Worme is as immortall as our ſelves. Wee may de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperately ſend our ſoules from our bodies: but
<pb n="263" facs="tcp:1458:176"/>ſinne and conſcience cannot be diſmiſſed. We may ſoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner part with our ſelves than with our tormentors. It were well a man might be as a flint in a rocke of ſtone, which as it findes no plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, ſo it feeles no paine: but this will not be gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, his wounded Spirit will never leave him, <hi>Prov.</hi> 18.14. A man ſuſtained by the Spirit of God, may beare any infirmitie: but when his owne ſpirit is as much wounded by God as him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, what man ſhall beare it? Once againe remember the Goſpel, and let it helpe and heale this miſery.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="264" facs="tcp:1458:177"/>
               <head>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>tter perdition.</head>
               <p>Wee often pitty men when we heare Briefes of utter undoing, and we com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly complaine of lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table loſſes, as if all were gone when we have parted with no more than our worldly goods. Never thinke men of being undone in ſpirituall loſſes. There is not the pooreſt Begger in the world, but in loſing his ſoule, he leaveth more than a King that is caſt out of his kingdome; nay, his loſſe is greater than to loſe the whole world. Better the ſoule bee ſaved, than a world purchaſed; and yet ſottiſh ſinners to ſeeke
<pb n="265" facs="tcp:1458:177"/>wealth upon earth, will haz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard their ſoules. I loſe my goods, yet I am not ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly undone as long as I have friends. I loſe my friends, yet I am not utterly undone, as long as I have my ſelfe. I loſe my life, yet ſtill I am farre from being undone, as long as God ſtands by me. But then I am undone indeed, when I have loſt God, then have I loſt my ſelfe. And all good Chriſtians, once more heare me friendly and favoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly: feare God, love his Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, live well, and never feare to dye ill. Many wretches feare to ſuffer ill, that never feare to ſinne, and of evils they ever feare the leaſt, loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king to their temporall life,
<pb n="266" facs="tcp:1458:178"/>and never regarding their ſpirituall. Thouſands feare to dye a corporall death, that never heed what it is to die an eternall. Feare were better placed upon ſinne than ſorrow. If wee would feare to ſinne, wee ſhould not need to feare to ſuffer; and in ſuffering wee were better place our feare upon the ſecond than firſt death. Vtter perdition is not in this world, that is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved for the day of death, and dungeon of hell.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The miſery of the place.</head>
               <p>It is ſometimes called a priſon, and judge what an hell it were to live and lie in a dungeon with Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters
<pb n="267" facs="tcp:1458:178"/>of men in this world. It is <hi>Tartarus</hi> of <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, a <hi>Pagan</hi> name, for fearefull and formidable Spectacles. They have imagined hell full of horrour for ſuch ſhapes and ſhadowes as they have fancied and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled by their Poets: but thoſe are poore affright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to the dreadfull and terrible face of God and his frowning countenance. Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience will skarre them more than ſhadowes, and darkeneſſe, than doating dreames. It is <hi>Tophet</hi> or <hi>Gehenna,</hi> a mercileſſe place. Infants yelling in the fire of <hi>Gehenna,</hi> had their voyces, cryings and ſhri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kings drowned by Drums from being heard of their
<pb n="268" facs="tcp:1458:179"/>parents. The brands of Hell may roare in the Lake, and none will bee found to pitty them. They cry too late, the doore of mercy being ſhut againſt them, and God of heaven turned their irreconcileable ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Extreame lamentation.</head>
               <p>They ſhall weepe their bellies <hi>full,</hi> and to weeping adde wailing, and wiſhing they had never beene. They ſhall wring their hands and curſe the day they were ever borne. And when ſorrow ſhall doe no good, gnaſh their teeth and grinde them againſt God for their exceſſive
<pb n="269" facs="tcp:1458:179"/>plagues. Teares ſhall not be taken for repentance, but ſerve to coole the heart and dant the ſpirits, ſo that extremity of cold may make their teeth chatter and gnaſh together. Heat and cold with all exceſſes and aggravations of ſorrow may meet together. We have but lightly touched what they muſt deepely taſte; would God it might teach us by ſo miſerable an end to make a happy beginning of our ſalvation and ſubje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to the Goſpell in this world. I will now diſpatch the reſt more briefely and wiſh thee the benefit in the whole.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="270" facs="tcp:1458:180"/>
               <head>Vnknowne miſery.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Peter</hi> queſtioneth what we quarrell withall, and ſay hell is not ſo hot as Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers make it. <hi>Peter</hi> knowes not how to make it hot enough. He had rather aske the queſtion and ſay, What ſhall the end be, than deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine. It were ſome com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort to a ſubject of hell to know his worſt. Men ſo ſolace their ſoules upon earth, with a ſtubborne re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution to their tormen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, doe your worſt, I know what you can doe, and there is an end: but it will not be ſo in hell, their ſturdy ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mackes muſt come downe, and not dare the Almighty
<pb n="271" facs="tcp:1458:180"/>to the tryall of his ſtrength. The reaſons why in hell men ſhall never faddom the bottome of their woes, are theſe; firſt, he that ſmites is infinite, and therefore can augment every blow hee gives. Wee whip our children often till they bee ſenſeleſſe and careleſſe of the rod: but God will worke them feeling, as well as whipping, and if need be, by an unwonted blow fetch bloud out of another veine. Men ſhall ſooner be weary with ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, than he with ſmiting, and every touch ſhall deare them more than other. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, man ſhall never know his owne capacitie. Hee hath enough to day to
<pb n="272" facs="tcp:1458:181"/>fill him to the brimme, his veſſell ſhall be ſtretched and ſtrained to hold as much or more the next day, and ſo for all eternitie hee ſhall be inlarged to receive torments. Thirdly, eterni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of extremity can never be brought to light; there is ſtill behind, whatſoever the meaſure be for the preſent. We onely that obey the Goſpell know our worſt, and what can be done for us in this world. happy time we ſuffered for God and his truth, that we may never ſuffer for ſinne in hell.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The confuſion of unbeleevers.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Where ſhall they appeare?</hi> Sinners and ungodly perſons
<pb n="273" facs="tcp:1458:181"/>ſhall be aſhamed to be ſeene, and ſhall finde no place where to hide their ſhame. A marveilous alteration ſhall befall them, and it ſhall be a wonder to ſee what a change is made in all their behaviour. Impudency and boldneſſe did attend them in all places, now feare and ſhame ſhall accompany them where ſoever they are. I will touch them in two things here related, their appearance and place: as no ground can hold them from trembling; ſo no ſight but it will put them to ſhame.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="274" facs="tcp:1458:182"/>
               <head>The appearance of unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leevers.</head>
               <p>It can hardly be credited with what audacious bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and bold audacity, men and women, dare ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare before God in this world, not once thinking that they are either in his debt or danger. They pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare not for their audite and account. They are like that impudent Ruffian that pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctured upon his Target God and the Devill, with an inſcription under both. Vnder God was written, <hi>ſi tu nolis,</hi> if thou wilt not have me, I am at a point with thee of defiance, &amp;c. Vnder the Devill, directly
<pb n="275" facs="tcp:1458:182"/>oppoſite to God, <hi>iſte rogitat,</hi> I am for the Divell and his ſervice. God muſt take them as they are; for they meane not to mend, and if hee like them not at their worſt, take them Divell. Men live as if they were ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to be happy here, or without hope hereafter. To gaine the world, they count all things lawfull, and judge they have nothing to injoy when they leave it. This makes them appeare empty before God, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhamed of their madneſſe and miſery.</p>
               <p>Our ſpeech and language might learne us the leſſon of our folly. We ſay when wee would be credited for certainty, <hi>It is as certaine as
<pb n="276" facs="tcp:1458:183"/>death,</hi> and then like fooles we croſſe our ſelves, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the ſtile when we have forgotten our ſelves, <hi>I did no more thinke of it than my death.</hi> I judge you by your owne mouthes, and mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt your madneſſe. You beleeve there is nothing that is more certaine than death, and confeſſe there is nothing you leſſe thinke of. <hi>As God ſhall judge mee,</hi> is as ready as words, and yet by workes you deny it, fearing nothing leſſe than his judgement. To contemne his Law, and deſpiſe his Goſpell, is your ordinary practiſe. He may command, you will not obey. He may threaten, you will not feare. He may
<pb n="277" facs="tcp:1458:183"/>promiſe you will not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve. His juſtice you dare affront, his mercy controul, his anger does but provoke you, his goodneſſe embol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens you to ſinne. You re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt and rebell againſt his Spirit, outface and diſgrace his Ordinances, rage and raile againſt his Miniſters, ſcoffe and ſcorne at your brethren, and there is not any wickedneſſe you bluſh at, or once checke or chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge your ſelves for the wrong you doe to God and men, Law and Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel.</p>
               <p>But tell me what you will doe, and how you will deale at your appearance and meeting with your judge: you have made others trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb n="278" facs="tcp:1458:184"/>defore you, and accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to your authority have lorded it over your inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours. Thinke ſeriouſly of your ſtanding before a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Lord, and gaine an Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocate to pleade with him. You ſhall not bee able to ſhew your faces, or open your mouthes without him. Laugh no longer (yee impudent ſinners) at your audacious practiſes, take counſell betimes. <hi>Bee affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, and mourne, and weepe; let your laughter be turned to mourning, and your joy to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vineſſe. Humble your ſelves in the fight of the Lord, and hee ſhall lift you up, Iam.</hi> 4.9, 10. Lift not up your ſelves and brow-beat his Ordinances, but beare downe the ſtout
<pb n="279" facs="tcp:1458:184"/>and ſtubborne heart to bee aſhamed betimes, and the Lord will encourage you in the evill day. Preſumptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous perſons will pricke on in their pride, and periſh in the end. It will be terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for them to appeare be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God, that never appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red before him in prayer, but alwayes againſt him. Thinke of this appearance and by the Goſpel make your preparation.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nbeleevers have no place free from feare.</head>
               <p>Where ſhall they ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare? They may not hide themſelves, and yet no place ſhall be ſafe for their appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance. They will be calling
<pb n="280" facs="tcp:1458:185"/>to rockes and mountaines to fall upon them and cover them from from the dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and irefull Iudge: But no hill will be intreated to hide them, no rocke to ruſh upon them. Miſerable wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches that can beare their ſinnes with eaſe, had rather lie under hards rockes and maſſie mountaines, than the leaſt touch of Gods wrath. <hi>Sampſon</hi> tooke the Gates of <hi>Gaza</hi> with the poſts and barres upon his ſhoulders, and bare them to the very top of the hill; ſuch ſtout <hi>Sampſons</hi> are our ſinners that ſtick at no ſinne, breake open the floud-gates of all impietie, pull up all poſts and barres that ſhould ſhut them up, and carry all down
<pb n="281" facs="tcp:1458:185"/>before them, and raiſe up to the very top of the hill, the hight of their horrible crimes. All places are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filed with their unclean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and they leave no roome in the earth for righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe to dwell in. Such as they brew, ſuch muſt they drinke, and God will not leave them a place where to ſhew their heads or ſhelter themſelves from danger. No Cave ſhall co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver them, no den of darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe keepe them from eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall darkeneſſe. I will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude with Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.11. <hi>Knowing therefore the terrour of the Lord, wee per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade men, but wee are made manifeſt to God, and trust al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, are made manifeſt in your
<pb n="282" facs="tcp:1458:186"/>conſciences.</hi> If the terrour of the Lord (as we have tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched it) were made manifeſt vnto men they would bee perſwaded: but, alas, it will never worke till men ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply it to their conſciences: in them have I laboured to fixe this worke, and have found ill hearers of it. My comfort ſhall be with aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance that to God wee are made manifeſt, we deale ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely, and wiſh it may worke kindly in all for their timely converſion, and holy converſation to the end, <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:1458:186"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
